<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The eunuche's conuersion A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the second of February. 1617. By Charles Sonnibank, Doctor of Diuinitie, &amp; Canon of Windsor.</title>
            <author>Sonibancke, Charles, 1564-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849355</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12604)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1497:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The eunuche's conuersion A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the second of February. 1617. By Charles Sonnibank, Doctor of Diuinitie, &amp; Canon of Windsor.</title>
                  <author>Sonibancke, Charles, 1564-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 135, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Richard Fleming; and are to be sould at his shop at the great south doore of Paules, on the right hand going vp the shops,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on A4v.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14496:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14496:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EVNVCHE'S CONVERSION.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at <hi>Paules</hi> Croſſe, the ſecond of February. 1617</p>
            <p>By <hi>Charles Sonnibank,</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, &amp; Canon of Windſor.</p>
            <figure>
               <q xml:lang="lat">COR VNVM VIA VNA</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Richard Fleming;</hi> and are to be ſould at his Shop at the great South doore of Paules, on the right hand going vp the ſteps. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14496:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14496:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, my worthie Friend, <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Allen,</hi> Eſquire, Sonne and Heire to the Right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>William Allen,</hi> Knight, ſometimes Lord Maior of <hi>the Honourable Citie of London, C. S.</hi> wiſheth all the bleſſings of this, and of the better life.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His meane labour and work of mine <hi>(Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and my worthie Friend)</hi> framed onely for the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> not for the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended onely to the eares, not to the eyes of men, had not at this time, in this ſhape and forme, preſented it ſelf to your view, If either I could haue ſatisfied the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie
<pb facs="tcp:14496:3"/> of many of my Friends, which did earnestly ſolicite me to print the ſame, or could haue preuented the purpoſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom without breach of charitie I may in ſome ſenſe tearme my Foes, who (as I had a watch-word giuen me) were minded, in caſe I could not bee thereunto entreated; to ſet forth in print thoſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and vnperfect notes, which they tooke from my mouth, at the time when I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered this Sermon.</p>
            <p>And here, I confeſſe, I was brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtrait, by my Friends on the one ſide, &amp; my Foes on the other: So that although I had long ſince put on a ſettled purpoſe, to publiſh no Pamphlets, in this <hi>Scribbling Age,</hi> wherein ſo much paper is blotted, and wherein ſo many, as ſoone as they haue but laid an egge, do preſently cackle, and bewray an itching humour of beeing in print; yet as one that had forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, I haue relapſed, and by a kinde of conſtraint haue fallen (as you ſee) from my firſt and beſt reſolution; and ſo by pleaſing others, haue diſpleaſed my ſelfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14496:3"/>
            <p>But, howſoeuer; I reſt aſſured, your loue to mee, will excuſe mee, and will take in good parte this <hi>Paper-Preſent,</hi> which reacheth out the hand vnto you, for acceptance: the rather, for that in one part and paſſage thereof, it putteth you &amp; others of your ranke in mind of that which <hi>You</hi> ſeldome forget, namely, that as God hath been very gratious to you, in bleſsing you, not only with great abundance of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſsings, nor onely with a wiſe &amp; vnderſtanding, but with a pious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious heart, and in theſe reſpects hath made you great; ſo you ſhould ſtriue by all means to bleſſe &amp; honor him, from whom you haue your greatneſſe: as alſo for that it commeth from ſuch a one, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is, that all they who vouchſafe to reade theſe lines ſhould knowe, that the Author of them, is one of thoſe many, which honour your Vertues, and loue your Perſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, in all Chriſtian offices of loue, CHARLES SONNIBANK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:14496:4"/>
            <head>The Authors Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>In page 114. line 14. theſe words, (1. Effect; <hi>He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued</hi>) would haue been placed in page 112. imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before the laſt line.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults of the Preſſe in ſome few Copies.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Page.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Line.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>10. &amp; 11. For <hi>comforth,</hi> read <hi>comfort.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>1. For <hi>their,</hi> read <hi>in their.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33.</cell>
                     <cell>17. For <hi>way,</hi> read <hi>may.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>94.</cell>
                     <cell>1. For <hi>came,</hi> read <hi>ranne.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>108.</cell>
                     <cell>5. For <hi>on-,</hi> read <hi>onely.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14496:4"/>
            <head>THE EVNVCH'S Conuerſion.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Acts 8.26.27.28. &amp;c.</bibl>
                  <p n="26">
                     <hi>26.</hi> Then the Angel of the Lord ſpake vnto Philip, ſaying, Ariſe, and goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the South: vnto the way that goeth downe from Ieruſalem vnto Gaza, which is waſte.</p>
                  <p n="27">
                     <hi>27.</hi> And he aroſe and went on: and beholde, a certaine Eunuch of Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia, Candaces the Queene of the Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians chiefe gouernour, who had the rule of all her treaſure, and came to Ieruſalem to worſhip.</p>
                  <p n="28">
                     <hi>28.</hi> And as he returned ſitting in his chariot, he read Eſaias the Prophet. &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S we may cleerly ſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with the eyes of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies the power and goodneſs of God, in the creation of the worlde
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14496:5"/> by his Sonne, by whom hee made the world. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.2. So may wee with the eyes of our ſoules, much more cleerely ſee &amp; behold, his more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull omnipotencie and goodnes, in the recreating, and new making there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by the ſame his Sonne; by whom he remade, that is to ſay, he redeemed the world. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>In the former, <hi>Dixit &amp; formata ſunt omnia,</hi> Hee ſpake the word, and all things were formed; in the later, <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt Christus, &amp; reformata ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> Chriſt ſuffered, &amp; all things were made anew and reformed.</p>
            <p>In the former, hee ſhewed <hi>digitum potentiae,</hi> the finger of his power; in the later, hee ſhewed <hi>manum miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae,</hi> his whole hand of mercy.</p>
            <p>In the former, he breathed into the world the breath of life: in the later, it pleaſed him that his Sonne ſhould <hi>expirare,</hi> ſhould breathe out his owne breath, and lay downe his owne life for the world, that ſo it might haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14496:5"/> life. Thereby verefying vnto vs, the comfortable trueth of that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, which reuerend and Chriſtian antiquity hath from age, to age, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs; to wit, that God hath ſhewed himſelfe more glorious in redeeming, than in making the world and mankinde.</p>
            <p>Now, that this great work of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy wrought by God, in the perſon of Chriſt, for the ſaluation of man, might bee made knowne to all men; it pleaſed God to make that great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution mentioned in the beginning of this chapter, to be a very effectuall meanes.</p>
            <p>For whereas the godly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full beleeuers in Chriſt, were all ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as it were ſo many Bees in one Hiue; God beeing pleaſed that the hony &amp; ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his ſauing truth, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Sonne, ſhould be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhut vppe in that one Hiue, but ſhould bee imparted to others, both
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14496:6"/> men and nations, ſuffered them to be ſcattered and diſperſed, <hi>in ſimilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem granorum ſeminis, vt ex ipſis mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſeges fidei multiplicaretur,</hi> that ſo, of their ſowing the ſeedes of faith, &amp; of the knowledge of Chriſt, there might follow a great harueſt of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers vnto God. Which thing did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly fal out, <hi>Nam vt ex grano ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> as of one graine commeth a whole eare, and ſometimes many eares of corne: ſo was it in them, for many times one of their Sermons did beget and bring forth a multitude of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full beleeuers.</p>
            <p>Among thoſe faithfull beleeuers, which by reaſon of this great perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were driuen from Ieruſalem, &amp; beeing ſcattered abroad, went to and fro, preaching the word, as appeareth in the fourth &amp; fift verſes of this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Philip</hi> was one: not that <hi>Philippe</hi> which was one of the twelue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, for they all as appeareth in the firſt verſe of this chapter, ſtayed ſtill at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14496:6"/> Ieruſalem; but it was that <hi>Philip</hi> which is the ſecond in the Catalogue of the ſeauen Deacons, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.5.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Philip,</hi> after that hee had preached, and conuerted the City of <hi>Samaria,</hi> as it is ſet downe in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of this chapter, was imploied and vſed as you ſee in the wordes of my Text, for the conuerſion of this <hi>Eunuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The maine ſcope &amp; principall drift of the Spirit of God in this Scripture, and hiſtory, which I haue read vnto you, is to ſhew and ſhaddow out vnto vs, the large extent of the doctrine of the Goſpel, &amp; the kingdom of Chriſt, and how the ſame is by the counſell and mercifull purpoſe of God, to be propagated &amp; extended to the vtmoſt borders of the earth.</p>
            <p>And therefore in this preſent hiſtory, which I haue choſen at this time to treat of, you may bee pleaſed to beholde, how God vouchſafed to poure vpon the head of this <hi>Honorable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14496:7"/> Eunuch,</hi> the precious ointment of the ſauing knowledge of Chriſt: that like as the ſweete and precious oyntment that was powred on the head of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> ran downe from his head, and beard, to the skirts of his garments; ſo alſo this fragrant and ſweete oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, might ſtream downe, and flowe to the skirts as it were of his cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to the vtmoſt borders of his Countrie; and firſt to open to him the fountaine of life, and to let him drinke thereof; and then by him, as it were by a conduit pipe, to deriue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey the ſweete ſtreames and waters therof, to his countrie-men that dwelt a farre off, euen to the people and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Aethiopia.</hi> Which thing came accordingly to paſſe: for he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conuerted, conuerted many bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and as wee receiue it by tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, brought many of his owne nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the knowledge of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The chiefe and principall points which I obſerue in this Scripture, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14496:7"/> whereof I purpoſe by Gods aſsiſtance to ſpeake at this time, are theſe:
<list>
                  <item>1. An Angel diſpoſeth of <hi>Philip,</hi> &amp; aſsigneth him a place for his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. <hi>ver.</hi> 26.</item>
                  <item>2. Who, &amp; what he was, to whom, by the direction of the Angell, <hi>Philip</hi> was ſent. Firſt, hee was of <hi>Aethiopia.</hi> Secondly, hee was an honourable Perſonage chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor to the Queen of that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and had the rule of all, her treaſure. Thirdly, he came or he trauelled to Ieruſalem to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. <hi>ver.</hi> 27.</item>
                  <item>3. In the third place, wee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how this noble <hi>Eunuch</hi> was buſied &amp; emploied in his returne homeward: as hee returned ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his chariot, he read <hi>Eſaias</hi> the Prophet. <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</item>
                  <item>4. The fourth thing that I intend to ſpeake of, is <hi>Philips</hi> performance of that duty, and ſeruice, to which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14496:8"/> he was appointed. <hi>ver.</hi> 30.</item>
                  <item>5. Fiftly and laſtly, the effectes which his owne reading and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> preaching of Chriſt, wrought in this <hi>Eunuch;</hi> &amp; they are three: firſt, he beleeued: ſecondly, hee was baptiſed: and thirdly, after he beleeued and was baptiſed, he went homeward reioycing.</item>
               </list> In the firſt place, in that an Angel is appointed by God, to warne <hi>Philip</hi> to haſten and meete the <hi>Eunuch</hi> for his conuerſion, it may teach vs, how gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and mercifull God is to the ſons of men; who for their ſakes &amp; for their good, will haue his Angels to bee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable and helpfull vnto them.</p>
            <p>By the help of Angels, <hi>Lot</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, and preſerued in the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Sodome. ver.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>An Angel of God went before the hoaſt of Iſrael and behinde the hoaſt, and did deliuer them, &amp; defend them from the <hi>Egyptians. Exod.</hi> 14.19.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14496:8"/>
            <p>An Angell of the Lord opened the priſon doores by night, and brought forth the Apoſtles, and ſet them at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.19.</p>
            <p>An Angel directed <hi>Cornelius</hi> to ſend for <hi>Peter:</hi> and here an Angel is ſent to warne <hi>Philip</hi> to ioyne himſelfe to the Chariot of this Eunuch, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Scripture vnto him.</p>
            <p>So true is that of the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul, Angels are ministring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter for their ſakes vvhich ſhall be heires of ſaluation. Heb.</hi> 1. <hi>laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Happy are they, who by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, doe make a wiſe and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious vſe of the miniſtration of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; who by the cleanneſſe of their life, and holy conuerſation, make glad thoſe holy and bleſſed ſpirits, which are beholders and eye-witneſſes of all their actions; and by their vnfained repentance, giue them cauſe of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing: <hi>For there is ioy in the preſence of the Angels of God, for a ſinner that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth. Luke</hi> 15.10.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14496:9"/>
            <p>Which thing if wee ſhall doe, then ſhall thoſe Angels which reioyce in our wel-dooing, and are by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment content to loue vs, and to miniſter vnto vs heere <hi>in ſterquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio mundi,</hi> in this du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghill of the world, much more honour and loue vs, <hi>in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la coeli,</hi> in the Palace and kingdome of heauen; and beeing glad of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion in this life, will bee more glad of our aſſumption and ſaluation in heauen.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>In the ſecond or next place, we haue to conſider the perſon, to whom by the direction of the Angel, <hi>Philip</hi> was ſent; and hee is here ſaid, firſt, to be a man of <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any man ſhall vvonder how any ſparke of the knowledge &amp; true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, ſhould giue light, &amp; ſhine in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> by the light whereof this great and noble man might attaine to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14496:9"/> any glimſe of the knowledge of God, and thereby bee brought to deſire to performe any ſeruice and worſhip to him, and that in the place principallie appointed thereunto; namely, in his holy Temple, at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> eſpecially ſeeing that howſoeuer the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of preaching the Goſpel to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, though it were giuen &amp; ſealed to the Apoſtles and Diſciples, yet it was not yet ſped, or as yet execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</p>
               <p>If any man, I ſay, ſhall wonder here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at; he muſt knowe, that although the light of the Goſpell did not as yet ſhine, either in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> or in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and vtmoſt kingdoms of the earth: yet beſides that knowledge which men might haue by nature, and by the beholding of the creatures, and the frame of the world; the light of the law, and the knowledge of God, did in ſome proportion, either more or leſſe, ſhine or ſhimmer foorth to all Nations, <hi>ſingulis generum,</hi> though not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14496:10"/> 
                  <hi>generibus ſingulorum,</hi> as the Schoole ſpeaketh: to ſome of all Nations, though not to all particulars of euerie Nation.</p>
               <p>God hath not left himſelfe without witneſſes in any place; but hath left in all the Nations of the world, ſome prints &amp; footſteps of his knowledge, of his power, and goodnes.</p>
               <p>And although it might be ſaid, in regard of the eminencie thereof, that in <hi>Iurie</hi> God was well known, &amp; that his tabernacle was in <hi>Salem;</hi> yet was he knowne in other Nations alſo, and he made his Name glorious in all the quarters of the world.</p>
               <p>The prayer or wiſh of <hi>Noah,</hi> that <hi>Iaphet</hi> might dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> was in ſome meaſure in all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages, heard, and granted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gedeons</hi> fleece was not onely and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone watered, but the whole threſhing floore: the Land of <hi>Iury</hi> was not alone bedeawed &amp; moiſtned, with the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly deaw of the knowledge of God,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14496:10"/> but the whole earth, with the Nations that were farre remooued, euen to the vtmoſt bounds thereof.</p>
               <p>Some part of this heauenly deaw, might light vpon this Eunuch's head; and with ſome part of this holy oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his heart might be anointed.</p>
               <p>The bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Prophets, came into the hands, and Schooles of many of the Gentiles: &amp; not onely <hi>Plato,</hi> and many other of the more intelligent, &amp; better ſort of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, but Poets alſo, as <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> writeth, ſaw them: &amp; became as he ſpeaketh, <hi>Fures Moſis, &amp; Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum,</hi> theeues of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Prophets.</p>
               <p>And, howſoeuer the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth in the ninth to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> pertaineth the adoption, and the glory, and the couenants, and the giuing of the law, and the ſeruice of God; yet did it alſo pleaſe the Lord, that the knowledge of his law, and the manner of his holy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14496:11"/> worſhip and ſeruice, ſhould in ſome degree and proportion, and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times by diuerſe accidents and ſtrange meanes, bee deriued and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated in all ages, to Heathen men and Gentiles.</p>
               <p>So in the old Teſtament, by reaſon of the two great Captiuities of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelits,</hi> the one into <hi>Egypt,</hi> the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Babylon,</hi> the knowledge of God was ſpred in thoſe Nations: and from thence, both the Grecians and the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, fetcht a great part of their beſt, and moſt myſticall, and diuiner kinde of learning. And though the Iſraelites ſpoyled the Egyptians of their iewels, and other coſtly raiments, yet the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians ſpoyled the Iſraelites, of a far more precious iewell, euen the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true God.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee, how by all, or by ſome of theſe meanes, ſome glimſe, or portion of the knowledge of GOD, might come into <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this point. It was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14496:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> it was prayed for by <hi>Salomon,</hi> it was propheſied by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay,</hi> &amp; fore-told by <hi>Dauid,</hi> that ſtrange Nations ſhould knowe the Lord, and ſhould be made his ſonnes, and vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in his holy Temple.</p>
               <p>It was promiſed to <hi>Abraham, In thy ſeed ſhall all the Nations of the earth be bleſſed. Gene.</hi> 26.4.</p>
               <p>It was prayed for by <hi>Salomon</hi> (and mark I pray you, how <hi>Salomons</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reacheth, and fitteth the perſon of this Eunuch) <hi>Touching the Stranger,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, that is not of thy people</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>who ſhall come out of a far Country, for thy Names ſake, and ſhal come &amp; pray in this Houſe,</hi> (meaning the Temple) <hi>heare thou in Heauen, and doe according to all that the Stranger calleth for vnto thee.</hi> 3 <hi>Kings,</hi> 8.41.42.43.</p>
               <p>It was propheſied by <hi>Eſay, The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhall walke in thy light, and Kings at the brightnes of thy riſing vp: thy ſonnes ſhall come from far. Eſay</hi> 60.3.4.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Dauid</hi> more plainly and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14496:12"/> pointeth at this Eunuch's Country, &amp; ſaith; <hi>Aethiopia ſhal haſte to ſtretch her hand to God. Pſal.</hi> 68.31.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2</head>
               <p>Secondly, he is ſaid to haue been an honourable Perſonage; chiefe Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Treaſurer to the Queene of that Country of <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſheweth, that Nobilitie may ſtand with Chriſtianity; and that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and greatnes, riches &amp; vvealth, doe not in themſelues hinder men, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the knowledge, or from the worſhip and ſeruice of God.</p>
               <p>Although Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. <hi>that not many noble men, not manie mighty men, not many wiſe men after the fleſh, are called:</hi> yet he doth not exclude all noble men, all mightie men all wiſe men after the fleſh, from beeing called to the knowledge and ſeruice of God.</p>
               <p>For if all things come to paſſe by the direction and appointment of God;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14496:12"/> ſo that without him, not a ſparrovv lighteth on the ground. <hi>Math.</hi> 10.29. If euery good gift come from aboue, from the Father of lights, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17. If preferment come neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, but it is God that maketh lowe, and maketh high, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.6.7,</p>
               <p>Then to ſit at the ſtearn of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, and to guide King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to be borne of royall bloud, &amp; to come from the loynes of Princes, to ſit on ſeates of iudgement, &amp; from thence to miniſter iuſtice to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to be aduanced to the higheſt, or to the ſubordinate and inferior places of power, and authoritie, to be rich, and to haue this worlds goods in great abundance; euen all of theſe, and the like, they come not by chance, nor happen at aduenture; nor is it <hi>Catch that catch may,</hi> among the ſonnes of men: but it is the prouidence &amp; hand of God, that diſpenſeth them at his owne pleaſure, many times to them,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14496:13"/> to whom, with them, he giueth grace to vſe them to his glory, to the protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; defence of his Church, and to the behoofe and comfort of his Saints and ſeruants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Domini est terra, et plenitudo eius,</hi> The earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof; whether it be the fulneſſe of ſoueraigne authoritie &amp; princely dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, or the fulneſs of honor, &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſperity, or the fulneſſe of wealth, of riches, or temporall abundance: all theſe, and the like, as they come from God, and are in themſelues, rich gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, excellent ornaments, and euident arguments of Gods gracious goodnes and fauour to them, whom before, &amp; aboue others, hee there-with bleſſeth: ſo are they alſo, if in the vſe of them, they be ſanctified to the owners of them excellent means of doing good, and of glorifying God, in the gracious vſe, and imployment of them.</p>
               <p>He was a noble man, he was chiefe Treaſurer to a Queene, a verie great
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14496:13"/> man in his country, &amp; yet he was alſo the ſeruant of God. Nay, as he was ſo are all ſuch as are noble, &amp; great, and rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that they are noble, &amp; great &amp; rich, the better fitted, and the more bound to be the ſeruants of God.</p>
               <p>The better fitted. For gold &amp; ſiluer are metals far more fit to be wrought, and to haue precious ſtones ſet &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in them, than lead, or iron: ſo are the mindes of noble, and great, and rich men, for the moſt part more fit to receiue into them, the rich and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious graces &amp; the gifts of God, than thoſe that are vulgar men, &amp; of meane condition.</p>
               <p>And as they are for the moſt part better fitted than others; ſo are they more bound than others, to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>In a ciuill life this is the greateſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>Meus ſum,</hi> I am mine owne man, and at liberty: but in a Chriſtian life this is the greateſt comfort, euen of the moſt noble and greateſt perſons,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14496:14"/> 
                  <hi>Non ſum meus,</hi> I am not mine owne man, but Ieſus Chriſts, vvho hath bought mee with a price, and hath therefore bound mee, to glorifie and to ſerue him.</p>
               <p>It is a true ſaying, that <hi>Maior</hi> muſt be <hi>Melior;</hi> the greater muſt be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and to whom God giueth moſt, at his hands he wil require moſt.</p>
               <p>As therefore mortall men, are moſt bound to honour God moſt, becauſe they are the excellenteſt of all mortall creatures: ſo thoſe amongſt mortall men, who are noble, or rich, or great men, either by birth, or by imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or by their endeauours in the places where they liue, are moſt bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſerue God moſt, becauſe they are moſt excellent among mortall men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nobilitas ad virtutem obligat,</hi> nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie bindes men as it were in an obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be vertuous: and he that hath loſt his vertue, hath broken his bond, hath loſt his nobilitie, <hi>argentum ſuum in ſcoriam conuertit;</hi> hee hath changed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14496:14"/> his ſiluer into droſſe.</p>
               <p>The chiefeſt honour of a Noble, or great man, is vertue: and the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt vertue, is religion; without the which, how great ſoeuer hee bee at home, or abroad, and how noble ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he may ſeeme in his owne eyes, yet is hee baſe, and vile in the eyes of God.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> after that the people had forſaken God, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, They haue changed their glory, for that which doth not profit: as though the glory of a people, were indeed the ſeruice of the true God; and the ceaſing ſo to ſerue him, vvere the ceaſing, or looſing of their glory.</p>
               <p>The feare of the Lord, ſaith the wiſe ſonne of <hi>Sirach,</hi> in his firſt chapter, is a glory to a man, and a ioyfull crowne vnto his head.</p>
               <p>A King may be a King: but if hee want this feare, he is a King, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a crowne. A noble man may be noble: but without this feare, he ſhall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14496:15"/> want his glory. A great man may be great, either in his own, or other mens eyes: but if he want the feare of God, his greatnes is but as the ſwelling of a bladder puft vp with wind, which ſhal quickly vaniſh, and come to nothing. A rich man may be rich, and may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound &amp; euen wallow in wealth: yet if he be not rich in the Lord, &amp; walke not in his feare, his riches are but as the varniſh vpon a rotten poſt: hee is painted indeed with gold, but his root is rottenneſſe, his life is ſinful, and his end inglorious.</p>
               <p>For the richeſt crowne, and chiefeſt glory to great men, in what kinde ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be great, is the fear and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God: their greateſt preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue is to be of the houſhold of faith: their greateſt freedom is to be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God: their greateſt nobilitie is their new birth in Chriſt: and their greateſt riches, are the gifts and graces of Gods Spirit in them.</p>
               <p>At the top of the ſcepter, and of all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14496:15"/> greatnes, ſits Honor, and at the foote of the ſcepter, and of all greatnes, ſits Care; not onely the care of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſuch duties as belong to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch as are any way great, but eſpecially the care of ſeruing and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, from whom they haue their greatneſſe: without which care, honour is but as a bundle of painted flowers, that yeeld no true ſweetneſſe; and greatneſſe is but as a bunch vpon the back of a deformed creature, which makes him the more misſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and lothſome in the eyes of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauids</hi> glory, was the Lord. <hi>Thou, O Lord</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>art my buckler, the lifter vp of my head, and my glory. Pſal.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperor hold it a greater honour vnto himſelfe that he was <hi>Membrum Eccleſiae,</hi> than that he was <hi>Caput Imperij;</hi> that hee vvas a member of the Church, and thereby the ſeruant of God, than that hee was the head, and Commaunder of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14496:16"/> whole Empire.</p>
               <p>And I am verely perſwaded, that our moſt Chriſtian and princely <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius,</hi> doth more reioyce, and dooth herein take more comfort, that hee is <hi>Defenſor fidei,</hi> Defender of the true, ancient, truly Catholique &amp; Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſaith, than that he is <hi>Magnae Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniae Rex,</hi> the ſole Monarch, &amp; great Commander of <hi>Great Britaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſurely heerin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, &amp; for this we haue great cauſe to praiſe GOD, for that our nobleſt plants, both root, &amp; branches, planted by the Lords owne right hand, in the beſt &amp; fatteſt grounds of our country, who haue the beſt title &amp; greateſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt among vs to true nobility &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, doe like vnto the fruitfull trees of Paradiſe, bring foorth among vs, not onely much hope, but much fruite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of holineſſe, and religious pietie, to the glory of God that heere hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them.</p>
               <p>And as they for their parts, ſo it is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14496:16"/> farther alſo to be wiſhed, that all they which are great, in a ſubordinate, and inferiour degree of greatneſſe vnto them, the greater they are, the more they alſo would acknowledge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bound, &amp; the more they would ſtriue to worſhip and ſerue God, who hath made them great; that ſo it might be truly ſaide in our Church, &amp; this Common-wealth, that not onely <hi>Terra dat fructu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuum,</hi> the earth brings forth her increaſe, when poore men doe gladly ſerue God, but alſo that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Coeli enarrant gloriam Dei, &amp; astra matutina laudant eum:</hi> that is, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſet forth the glory of God, and the morning ſtars praiſe him; when our greateſt Grandoes, our nobleſt, &amp; our chiefeſt great-ones, are carefull to ſerue, and to feare the Lord.</p>
               <p>And here me thinkes, I haue a very fit and iuſt occaſion offered me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtraining, or offering violence to my Text, to ſpeake vnto you Right Honourable, whether you ſit on the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14496:17"/> one, or the other bench, and to you Right Worſhipfull, whereſoeuer you are ſeated, and howſoeuer you be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that heare me this day, euen to as many of you, as either for your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, your office, or your wealth, haue prime and principall places in this our Common-wealth; and firſt, by the example of this honourable &amp; rich Eunuch, to tel you for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, that your greatneſſe and plentie, may ſtand with the ſeruice of God, &amp; Chriſtianity; and next, for your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter remembring thereof, to put you all in minde, that by how much the more God hath beene bountifull to you aboue other men, by ſo much the more you ought and are bound aboue other men, to be dutifull, and ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto him, becauſe that from the ſea of his bounty, you haue receiued all your waters, from the torch-light of his goodneſſe, you haue lighted all your candles, from the fountaine of his fauour, you haue filled all your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14496:17"/> pitchers, and from the Mine of his treaſures, you haue receiued all your riches.</p>
               <p>And therefore let mee ſpeake vnto you, that are mighty &amp; rich, and great men in this aſſembly, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did to the great men in his time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.1.1. <hi>Giue vnto the Lord, O yee mighty, giue vnto the Lord, glory, and ſtrength, giue vnto the Lord, the glory due vnto his name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing you cannot giue any actuall and reall ſeruice, any actuall &amp; reall workes of bounty, or requitall, to the perſon of God himſelfe, both for that he is in heauen, and needeth nothing that is yours; yet doe them to the ſupport of Gods trueth, and the furtherance of religion, do them to the maintenance of ſtudy, and increaſe of learning, doe them to Chriſts needy Saints and poore children; and then know it, &amp; remember it to your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that what you doe to them, you doe to Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14496:18"/> who will not leaue you vnrewarded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he could not be kind, nor ſhew his loue to <hi>Ionathan</hi> his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friend, he ſhewed it to poore and lame <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than:</hi> ſo ſeeing you cannot ſhew kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to your Lord and Sauiour, Ieſus himſelfe, ſhew it to his lame <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth's,</hi> his lame, his poore, his indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and needy Saints, and ſeruants.</p>
               <p>Some write, that although the gold, myrrh, and frankincenſe, which were offered by the Wiſe men, to our Sauiour Chriſt, were not receiued by him into his owne hands, becauſe hee was an Infant, but into the hands of his Mother; that yet neuertheleſſe, he gaue vnto the Wiſe men that offered him thoſe gifts, <hi>Pro auro fidem, pro myrrha ſpem, pro thure charitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> for the gift of golde, the vertue of faith; for the gift of myrrh, the vertue of hope; &amp; for the gift of frankincenſe, the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of charity. And why may not we likewiſe ſay, that although thoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14496:18"/> bleſsings, which by honourable, or rich, or great men, are offered to Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, in his poore members, or are beſtowed to pious and good vſes, that though they bee receiued onely by the hand of their Mother, the Church; yet for all that, Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe will gratiouſly and plentifully, reward the giuers of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3</head>
               <p>The third, or the next thing, which I noted in the perſon of this noble <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch</hi> is, that hee came from his owne Countrie to Ieruſalem, to worſhip.</p>
               <p>He might haue ſtayed at home, and ſo haue ſaued himſelfe a great iourney, hee might haue ſacrificed to the Gods of his owne Nation, and there haue had other Noblemen of his owne ranke, to aſſociate him.</p>
               <p>Hee might haue worſhipped in Meroe, the chiefe and Metropolitan
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14496:19"/> Citie of Aethiopia, and needed not to trauell ſo far as Ieruſalem, the chiefe and mother Citie of Iudaea.</p>
               <p>But he could not ſo ſatisfie himſelf, the Spirit of God wrought another e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect in him: and that light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which he had by the operation of the ſame Spirit, which now had changed him into another man, did to affect him, and worke with him, that now no Country but the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of Iudaea, no Hill but the Hill of Sion, no Place but the Temple, no Citie but the Citie of Ieruſalem, no God but the God of Iſrael, could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the large extent of his deuotion, could fill the deſires of his heart, and ſatisfie his ſoule with comfort.</p>
               <p>It was not contentment enough for him, to wiſh with the Prophet <hi>Dauid, O that I might aſcend into the houſe of the Lord, and come againe vnto Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, there to pay my vowes to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,</hi> and ſo to goe thither in conceit onely.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:14496:19"/>
               <p>It did not ſufficiently content him, with the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> to ſet open thoſe his windowes which were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the holy Citie, and looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Ieruſalem, to direct his prayers to the Almighty.</p>
               <p>It could not ſufficiently content him, to make a proxie, to ſend giftes, and to viſit Ieruſalem by his deputie: but though the iourney were long, the way dangerous, and the expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces great; yet would hee vndertake the iourney, and goe his owne ſelfe in perſon thither. <hi>Hee went vp to Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem to worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although it could not chooſe, but prooue a matter of hatred at the leaſt, if not of danger, and diſgrace, to this noble Eunuch, to entertaine a new forme of Gods worſhippe, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that which was vſed by his owne Nation, to renounce the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of his Countie-men, to ſingle himſelfe from the multitude, and to refuſe to communicate with his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14496:20"/> and forefathers, their heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and idolatrous ſeruing of God: Yet did hee more eſteeme the fauour of God, then he feared the malice, or diſgrace of men: and therefore the reuerence and loue which he did bear inwardly in his heart towards the law, and truth of God, and his holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, hee ſhewed it outwardly in his actions, &amp; openly profeſſed the ſame before men:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee went vp to Ieruſalem to worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An excellent example, and worthie imitation, not onely of great men, and noble perſonages, but of all men, of what degree, or calling ſoeuer they be; In the matter of religion, and the ſeruice and worſhip of God, not to tie themſelues to tread in the ſteps of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not to bee ſwayed by a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, nor to follow their Anceſtors and Forefathers in their errours and ſuperſtitions; but moſt humbly and moſt willingly, to embrace the true
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14496:20"/> knowledge, and ſincere worſhippe of God, whenſoeuer, and by whom ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is truly taught, and brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
               <p>A leſſon not vnfit for theſe times, and this Age, wherein wee liue, in which our aduerſaries the Papiſts do ſo commonly vrge, and ſo ſtrongly inforce the example of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and Forefathers, againſt vs; thereby concluding, that becauſe they were borne and brought vp liued, &amp; died (as they ſpeake) in the Romiſh religion, that therefore we ought not to diſſent from them; and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the blot &amp; imputation of Schiſm and hereſie, wee <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay in no wiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate our ſelues from their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or profeſſe any other faith, than that which they profeſſed.</p>
               <p>And to ſpeake a truth, I am hereof verely perſwaded, that by this, as by their moſt powerfull and potent charme, they doe bewitch, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant more ſoules, eſpecially, of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14496:21"/> weaker ſort, than by all their other ſorceries whatſoever: and by this, as by their ſtrongeſt argument, they do much preuaile, and draw many from <hi>Iewry</hi> to <hi>Italy,</hi> from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this motiue eſpecially, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that heere in this our Land (as it may bee obſerued) great and whole Families, great and whole Kindreds almoſt, haue been, and doe continue Popiſh, becauſe their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Forefathers were ſo before them, and becauſe it were great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in them, as they are made beleeue, to thinke themſelues wiſer, than They were.</p>
               <p>But if this were an vniuerſall, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and certaine truth, that fathers muſt be patterns, and rules for their children to ſerue God by, ſo that in no wiſe they may differ from them, in matters of Gods worſhip; then how is it that our Sauiour ſaith, in the 14. of <hi>Luke</hi> the 26. that <hi>He, that will not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14496:21"/> leaue his father, and his mother, for Chriſts ſake, ſhould not be his diſciple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When all the Tribes reuolted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſaith <hi>Tobit,</hi> and the houſe of my father <hi>Nepththali,</hi> ſacrificed to the heifer <hi>Baal,</hi> I alone went often to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, at the feaſts, as it was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto all the people of Iſrael. <hi>Tobit</hi> 1.5.6</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gedeon</hi> was commanded by the Lord, to throwe downe the Altar of <hi>Baal</hi> which his father had made, and to cut downe the Groue that was by it. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 6.25.</p>
               <p>And ſome of the Kings of Iuda are commended, becauſe they walked not in the Idolatrie of their Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was the ſonne of a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie, and the ſcholler of a Phariſie, &amp; yet neither Father, nor Maſter, could make him continue in the ſuperſtition of the Phariſies, after that hee was once illuminated, and inſtructed in the truth.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14496:22"/>
               <p>It is a wiſe, and and a godly ſpeech of <hi>Seneca, Epiſt.</hi> 117. when wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>diſſentire ſalua gratia,</hi> nor <hi>conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſalua conſcientia,</hi> when wee cannot diſſent from others, without their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, nor conſent vnto them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wounding or offending our owne conſcience, Let vs preferre conſcience before fauour.</p>
               <p>And it is a golden rule, which Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines haue reſolued on, and deliuered, <hi>Where God and man ſpeake both one thing, there harken vnto both: but where God ſpeaketh one thing, and man another, there harken to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a moſt Chriſtian, and worthy anſwere, fitting this preſent purpoſe, worthy of all your attention and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, which was giuen by <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian</hi> the Emperour, to <hi>Symmachus,</hi> which is recorded in the fift booke of Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his <hi>Epiſt. Symmachus</hi> a heathen man, and in all likelihood, an excellent Oratour, ſuch a one as was <hi>Tertullus,</hi> of whom there is mention,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14496:22"/> 
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24. hauing penned an eloquent ſpeech, the ſcope and purpoſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, was, to perſwade the Emperour that embraced the Chriſtian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe, and was reſolued to haue the ſame receiued, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his Empire, that he would bee pleaſed, to permit the ancient Citie of Rome, to hold her olde forme, and to keepe and vſe the olde manner of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing her heatheniſh Gods; thus he tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his pipes, and thus he beſpake the Emperour.</p>
               <p>Regard ſaith Rome mine age, which haue now ſtood a thouſand yeares, and ſhall I now at the laſt, be checked and controuled, in my olde dayes? This religion which wee now ſeeke for, &amp; ſue for at thy hands, O Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, was that, which won to Rome the ſoueraignty of the earth, which repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and beat back that cruell <hi>Hannibal,</hi> from ſcaling of our walls, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued our goodly <hi>Capitoll</hi> out of the French mens hands: And now it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14496:23"/> were a reproach after ſo long time, &amp; ſo many Ages, to haue it quite reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Much more was ſpoken, all very ſuiteable and like, if you marke it, to the diſcourſes, and ſpeeches of our Papiſts: but for an vp-ſhoot, and for a concluding argument, that was at laſt brought in, that his owne Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, had ſuffered them to enioy that forme and manner of ſeruing their Gods, and neuer diſallowed it, and therefore it was his part to permit it ſo likewiſe.</p>
               <p>But the worthie Emperour, as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſaith, in his funerall Sermon vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, beeing reſolutely addicted to the defence, and maintenance of Chriſts glory, made this anſwere; Let Rome my Mother intreate any thing elſe at my hands, and aske what elſe ſhe will of me: I owe vnto her I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe a very great dutie, and affection, becauſe ſhe is my Mother, but I doe owe a greater to God my Father, who is the author of my ſaluation.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14496:23"/>
               <p>This was a worthie anſwere, of a worthie Prince: from whence wee may learne this inſtruction, In matters which concerne the glory and ſeruice of God, not to ſtand vpon the will or words of men, but onely on this only point, <hi>Sic dicit Dominus,</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, and with thankfulneſſe to receiue his trueth, whenſoeuer it is brought vnto vs.</p>
               <p>And ſurely, if our ancient Fathers, the olde and firſt Chriſtened Gentiles, of this our Iland of <hi>Great Britanne,</hi> &amp; other faithleſſe at the firſt, and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Kingdomes,</hi> had not held this rule, and kept this courſe, when it pleaſed God in great mercy, that the Goſpell of his Sonne Chriſt, and his ſauing truth was firſt brought vnto them; then might they, and we, ſtill haue remained in our ignorance and infidelitie; then ſhould they, and wee, haue continued aliens from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of Iſrael, ſtrangers to the couenants of grace, bondſlaues to ſin
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14496:24"/> and Satan, not onely depriued of that glorious name, by which we are called Chriſtians, of Chriſt, but alſo debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from hauing any part or portion in that great worke of mercy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, which was wrought by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>For, they might haue replied to them, that were the firſt meſſengers and preachers, which firſt brought vnto them the glad tidings of the Goſpell, and haue ſaide vnto them, as the Athenians did to Saint <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 17.18. <hi>What will this babbler ſay? hee ſeemeth to bee a ſetter forth of ſtrange gods, in that he preacheth vnto vs Ieſus, and the reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They might haue ſaid vnto them, Our Fathers worſhipt the Queene of heauen, they beleeued on <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> they ſacrificed to <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> they worſhipped the Moone, and the Starres, and ſo did their Fathers, and great Grandfathers and Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, ſome thouſands of yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14496:24"/> them: and ſhall we now begin to liſten to a new and vp-ſtart Religion; and renouncing thoſe ancient Gods, that they ſo long ſerued, controll their iudgement, and ſo admit of a new-found doctrine, &amp; worſhip new-found Gods?</p>
               <p>But it pleaſed God to mooue their hearts, to receiue with meekneſſe that truth; and ſo by ſucceſsion, to deriue vnto vs that truth, which was, and is able, to ſaue both theirs, and our ſoules.</p>
               <p>You ſee, Right honourable, Right worſhipfull, and beloued in the louer of your ſoules, Chriſt Ieſus, to vvhat iſſue this point is brought, and what it is that I ayme at: namely, that as this noble Eunuch renounced the Idolatry of his Country, and the ſuperſtitions of his Anceſtors and Forefathers; not ſuffering them to be a rule, or making them a preſident to himſelfe, either for his faith, or for his manner of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, but went vp to Ieruſalem,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14496:25"/> there to worſhip him in his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: ſo it is the duty of all men, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all falſe &amp; ſuperſtitious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and to entertaine his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truth, whenſoeuer, and by whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it is reuealed, and brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, how many ſoeuer, or how mighty ſoeuer, or how neere or deere ſoeuer they be vnto them, that do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance and withſtand the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now, although this be a moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, and that our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries doe knowe it in their conſciences ſo to be, yet doe they neuer giue ouer to obiect, and with a full mouth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime againſt vs, filling the ayre, and the eares of men, with theſe, and the like frequent queſtions, &amp; demaunds; What? were all our Anceſtors and Forefathers deceiued? liued they all in error? did they all of them miſſe, and miſtake the meanes which leade vnto ſaluation, and by conſequent did they all miſſe the end? Did ſo many milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them periſh, and vvere they all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14496:25"/> damned?</p>
               <p>In anſwer of which their demands, which they ſo willingly and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make, and by which they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled many ſoules, eſpecially of the ſimpler ſort, and ſuch as are vnlearned, carying them away captiue, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them bondſlaues to the man of ſinne, the Antichriſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> I will lay downe theſe three propoſitions.</p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>1. <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Firſt: <hi>They were not all Papiſts that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the time of Popery; and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, all our Anceſtors and Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were not Papiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly: <hi>They did not all die Papiſts that in their life time were Papiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly: <hi>Some that both liued, and died Papiſts in many points, yet holding the principall, and fundamentall parts of Gods bleſſed, and holy truth, might be, and vvere alſo ſaued.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And firſt, not to ſpeake of the firſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14496:26"/> ſix or ſeauen hundred yeeres after Chriſt, which were the purer times of the primitiue Church, in which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the name of <hi>Pope,</hi> nor the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and points of Popery, as now they are held, had any beeing or foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Church: if we ſhall deſcend to the lower and later ages and times, wherein Popery, or the religion of <hi>Rome,</hi> grew ſtrong, and held her head at the higheſt; wee ſhall finde, if with a ſingle eye and without partialitie wee enquire thereinto, that as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, ſo in all ſucceeding ages &amp; times, euen to this of ours, there was a Church of our Religion.</p>
                  <p>And although the Profeſſors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of could not poſſeſſe whole Nations, or Countries, or Cities, wherin they might freely &amp; openly profeſſe their faith, by reaſon of the great height &amp; tyranny of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which not onely obſcured them, but did alſo cruelly perſecute them:</p>
                  <p>Yet were there few Nations, fevv
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14496:26"/> Countries, few Citties, wherein there were not ſome from time to time, yea and that alſo in the very boſome and midſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that did learnedly and zealouſly, and with the loſſe many times of their liues, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſame.</p>
                  <p>If any man ſhall heere call vpon vs to make a particular and preciſe bed-roll or catalogue of their names, and aske vs who they vvere that ſo haue done: I anſwere, that beſides all thoſe which liuing in former ages, and in the times of Popery, who either could not, by reaſon they were vnlearned, be known publiquely, &amp; to the world, but onely to God, and to their ovvne conſciences, to bee profeſſors of our Religion; or if they were learned, did yet commit nothing to writing, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſame might be known of them: I ſay beſides all thoſe, whoſe number no doubt was infinite, great is the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe godly and learned men, of thoſe faithfull witneſſes, which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14496:27"/> time to time, both by writing, by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and by dying, haue ſhewed to the world, that they groned vnder the burthen of Popery, that they wiſhed a reformation, and that they were of our Church, and profeſſed our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p>The names of which men, with the times in which they liued, together with thoſe paſſages, and parts of their bookes and writings, in which they witneſſe that which I haue affirmed of them, are collected together, and ſet downe by many learned men of our part; and therefore I will ſpare my ſelfe the labour of naming them vnto you at this time.</p>
                  <p>If any man ſhall further except and ſay, They are but few that are named, in compariſon of the reſt; &amp; that their number is ſmall: let ſuch a one know, that the number is not ſmall; and if it were, yet that it is no maruell that ſo few are named: it is rather a maruell that ſo many are named; ſeeing that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14496:27"/> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath in all ages &amp; times, ſo earneſtly laboured to blot out, and to deface the memory of all, both men, and matters, which might ſpeake for vs, or beare witneſſe vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>For, if at this day, our Aduerſaries wipe our very names out of bookes, and command that no man ſhall name vs but in contempt; wee may well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelues, that their Anceſtors haue done the like in former ages, to the men of our Religion: and hence it commeth, that ſo few are mentioned and named in ancient ſtories.</p>
                  <p>The practice of the Papiſts at this day with vs, defacing our names, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying our opinions, burying our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory corrupting our books, ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the truth of things, purging and razing all manner of Euidence, by that diueliſh deuice of their <hi>Indices expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorij,</hi> their purging tables, maketh vs aſſure our ſelues, that in the ſame manner our Anceſtors were vſed. And
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14496:28"/> this is a principall reaſon why wee yeeld not ſo perfect a catalogue as elſe we might doe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>2. <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>My ſecond propoſition vvhich I deliuered, was this; that <hi>They did not all die Papists, which in their life time, and in outward profeſsion were Papiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For, ſeeing it pleaſeth God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, euen at the eleuenth howre, to call men to the knowledge of himſelf, and to repentance; and ſeeing Gods mercy is not bounded, or confined to any times; but that as hee will haue mercy, on whom he wil haue mercy; ſo alſo hee will ſhew mercy, at vvhat time it pleaſeth him to ſhevv mercie; VVho can tell but that many of our Anceſtors and forefathers, being tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in conſcience, and renouncing themſelues, and all humane ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, haue at the time of their diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; the approching of death, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14496:28"/> their mindes; and ſo in that faith and religion which wee profeſſe, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp their ſoules into the hands of God.</p>
                  <p>A thing the more probable, and like to bee true, becauſe in theſe our dayes, many <hi>Papiſts</hi> haue bin by moſt certaine and true experience, obſerued to haue done, and to do the like: who in <hi>articulo mortis,</hi> beeing at the brink and point of death, haue been content, not onely to ſuſpect, and feare, but to renounce their own merits, and their owne works, to diſclaime the vvhole body of humane ſatisfactions, and to cleaue onely and alone, to the mercie of God in Chriſt, for their ſaluation; and ſo, though they liued <hi>Papiſts,</hi> haue died <hi>Protestants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And no maruaile though many <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> haue ſo done, and do ſo daily: for alas, what comfort or conſolation can a wounded conſcience, and a ſoule la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with ſinne, now ready to depart the vvorld, and to appeare before the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14496:29"/> maieſtie of GOD (in whoſe preſence the Cherubins are polluted, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are vnholy, and the heauens are vncleane) there to anſwere the iuſtice of God, and to giue an account for all things that it hath done in the bodie; I ſay what comfort or conſolation can ſuch a ſinfull and dying ſoule finde, in reflecting it ſelfe vpon it ſelfe, in the works of it owne hands, in the worth of it owne merites, in the fruites of it owne labours, in croſſes, crucifixes, Saints, <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> bleſſed graines, holy reliques, pilgrimages, extreame vnction, dirges, trentalls, maſſes, in Prieſts abſolutions, in Biſhops bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, in Popes pardons, or in all, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe, or other the traſh &amp; trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery of <hi>Rome?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Will ſuch Figge-leaues couer our ſhame? will ſuch ſacrifices ſatisfie for ſinne? or can ſuch ſtubble and ſtrawe endure the fierie triall of Gods iuſtice, and yet not be conſumed?</p>
                  <p>Fooliſh <hi>Semele,</hi> great was thy folly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14496:29"/> (and thou art worthily taxed, &amp; bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a marke of folly and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous indiſcretion, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Poets them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) for deſiring that <hi>Iupiter</hi> would in the ſelfe-ſame manner viſit thee at his next comming, in which hee vſed to viſite <hi>Iuno:</hi> by vvhich meanes it came to paſſe, that thou waſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amazed at his brightnes, but alſo by the lightning and thunder which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him, when he was in his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, waſt burnt vp quick, &amp; quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed: So may I truly ſay, and it is no poeticall fiction, but an vndoubted truth, which I am about to vtter to all proud Papiſts, proud Phariſees, and Iuſticiaries whatſoeuer, which gird themſelues with their owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and arme themſelues vvith their owne good deſeruings and merites, as it were with armour of proofe, and coats of ſteele: Fooliſh Papiſt, great is thy folly, &amp; thou art woorthily tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and branded with a marke of folly, and dangerous indiſcretion, who puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14496:30"/> vp with the winde of thine owne worth, and being tickled in thine own heart, with the wanton conceit of I wot not what proportionable agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, between thine owne proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent righteouſnes, and the iuſtice of God, dareſt to meet God in the face, and to confront his very iuſtice; and art ſo indifferent, that thou dooſt not much reckon, or greatly regard, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God, that is the Lord of glory, do come vnto thee in maieſtie, or in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, in the Law, or in the Goſpel, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and iuſtice, or in pitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, to iudge thy good works, in ſome of you, works of Supererogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and to giue ſentence of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which in many of you ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth, that as you beleeue, and teach others, they may reſerue enough for themſelues, and yet ſpare ſome for others, to make them alſo righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                  <p>And what maruaile is it, if beeing but duſt and aſhes, ſinfull fleſh, yea
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14496:30"/> ſtubble and ſtraw, fuell quickly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, his maieſtie amaze thee, and the fire of his iuſtice and iudgement, doe fearfully conſume thee?</p>
                  <p>Beloued in the Lord, it is dangerous building on the ſand. They build on the ſand, that make fleſh their arme; that put any confidence in their owne works. It is ſafe building on a Rock: they build on a rock, which build on Chriſt; <hi>The Rock is Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And, as <hi>Extra Arcam,</hi> without the Arke, the Doue found no reſt for the ſoale of her foote: ſo likewiſe, <hi>Extra Christum,</hi> without Chriſt, the ſoule of a ſinner can finde no comfort.</p>
                  <p>And bee it ſpoken to the glory of God, and to the honour of that truth, and that religion which wee profeſſe, This is that powerful motiue, and the very true cauſe, why ſo many that are profeſſed <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their life, doe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding at the approaching of death, and the very point of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, die <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> renouncing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14496:31"/> themſelues wholly, &amp; laying faſt hold onely vpon Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>I will trouble you but vvith tvvo inſtances or examples for the clearing of this point: the one, ancient; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, moderne, and of later time.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> lay ſicke, Doctor <hi>Day,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> comming to viſite him, began to comfort him, repeating to him ſome ſuch places of Scripture, as did expreſſe and import the free iuſtification of repentant ſinners, in the bloud of Chriſt. VVhereunto <hi>Winchester</hi> replyed; What, my Lord (quoth hee) vvill you open that gap now? then farewel all together: To mee, and ſuch other in my caſe, you may ſpeake it; but, open this window vnto the people, and then farewell all together.</p>
                  <p>When thoſe two vnholy and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Prieſts, <hi>Watſon,</hi> and <hi>Clark,</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered condigne puniſhment for the treaſonable practices whereof they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14496:31"/> were conuicted at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> ſome few yeeres ſince; the one of them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly, before hee was ready to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend the ladder, diſpoſing himſelfe to priuate prayer, was by two verie reuerend and eminent men of our Church (as one of them hath diuerſe times related it in my hearing) ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard to haue vſed theſe or the like words; O Lord (ſaid he) I haue not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to offer vp vnto thee, that is woorthy thy acceptance: I haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a corruptible carcaſſe, and a ſinfull ſoule to preſent vnto thee.</p>
                  <p>At his vttering of vvhich vvords, one of thoſe reuerend Diuines calling to the other; Harken, I pray you, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (ſaid hee) how hee diſableth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and renounceth his owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Which words when the Prieſt heard, hee breaking off the courſe of his prayer, made this reply to thoſe graue Diuines; Though (ſaid hee) I haue no merits to offer vp vnto God, yet it may be that many other of our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14496:32"/> religion haue merits, which both they may offer vnto God, and for vvhich, his Maieſtie may be graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be mercifull vnto them.</p>
                  <p>See, I pray you, how the truth of God preuailed with both theſe men, when their end drew neere, and when death approached: &amp; obſerue, I pray you farther, how they did in ſome ſort, diſclaiming all confidence in themſelues, and their owne merites, beare witneſſe to the truth of God, for the free iuſtification of ſinners onely by Chriſt. But whether or not, by their farther anſweres and replies, they laboured to hide that truth, and to put out that candle after it vvas lighted in them, I take not vpon mee to iudge, but doe leaue that to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>3. <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>My third propoſition which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, by occaſion of our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries demands, was this; <hi>All our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14496:32"/> periſhed not; neither were all our Forefathers, that liued in the time of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, damned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For firſt, ſome of them, which both liued and died Papiſts, in many points; yet holding the principall and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall parts, of Gods bleſſed and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truth, might be, and were alſo (as in the iudgement of charity, we may well thinke) partakers of ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is one thing to hold an error obſtinately, and wilfully, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the holding and profeſsing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with the hatred and perſecution of the truth: and another thing to erre ignorantly, being ſeduced by ſuch as are Paſtors and Teachers, with a minde notwithſtanding alway ready to embrace the trueth, whenſoeuer men ſhall bee further enlightened: And in this later kinde, many of our Anceſtors and Forefathers erred, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a minde alwaies ready, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be taught, though the ſtreame of the Times carried them away.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14496:33"/>
                  <p>Now as of the former ſort of theſe our Anceſtours, and Forefathers, which not onely erred in the capitall &amp; fundamentall parts of Gods truth, but erred wilfully, and obſtinately, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; preſecuting the truth vnto their death, we ſay, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>They periſhed, becauſe they receiued not the loue of the truth, that they might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10:</p>
                  <p>So in reſpect of the later ſort of them, we are farre from pronouncing the Sentence of damnation againſt them: we are not the Authors of any ſuch vncharitable, and peremptorie aſſertions, we vtterly diſclaime all ſuch black, and bloody concluſions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Geneſis</hi> 37.33. <hi>Iacob</hi> ſeeing the coat of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> rent, torne, and bloody, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out and ſaid, that <hi>Fera peſsima de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorauit eum, Some euill beast hath deuoured him;</hi> yet God prouided for <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and he was ſafe: So although the religion of our Forefathers, like the garment of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſeemeth rent,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14496:33"/> torne, and bloody vnto vs, and we in probability may cry and ſay, that <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra peſsima deuorauit eos,</hi> yet wee muſt not raſhly condemne them; becauſe God hath as wel extraordinary means to ſaue, as ordinary.</p>
                  <p>True it is, that many of our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers relied vpon the opinion of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and therefore were like to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who tooke money in their ſacks, when they went to Egypt for corne. But as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> returned them their money againe, and gaue them corne for nothing: ſo who can tell, but that God, giuing them grace at the laſt, to change their opinions, &amp; refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their merits, yet gaue them corn for nothing, accepting them in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued; and Chriſt, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> receiuing them as his brethren into eternall life.</p>
                  <p>As in charity wee are forbidden to thinke, that none of the Iſraelites en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into heauen, who entred not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy Land, or into the Land of Canaan, but died in the Wilderneſſe:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14496:34"/> ſo wee are not to thinke, that all thoſe our Forefathers periſhed, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the time of ignorance: but that, as many among vs, liuing in the light of the Goſpell, deſcend notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, into the darkneſſe of hell; ſo there were many liuing in the darknes of Poperie, who aſcended vp to the place of light, to the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and were partakers of eternall bleſſedneſſe.</p>
                  <p>To conclude this point: Let vs not raſhly enter into the iudgements of God: for he ſaith, <hi>I will haue mercy on whom I will haue mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sometimes God refuſeth the father, and chooſeth the ſonne; as in <hi>Salomon</hi> to build the Temple, and not <hi>Dauid:</hi> Sometimes hee ſheweth his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on the ſonnes, and mercy on the father; as in the children of <hi>Iob:</hi> Sometimes he cutteth off both the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the ſonnes; as he did <hi>Elie</hi> &amp; his children: Sometimes hee ſaueth both the father and his children; as
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14496:34"/> 
                     <hi>Noah</hi> and his children in the Arke: and this hee doth, to the end that be we fathers, or be we children, be wee many, or be we few, we ſhould learne to ſubmit our ſelues to him, and rather be carefull to obtaine our owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than to bee curious in the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſaluation of others.</p>
                  <p>I will cloſe and ſhut vp this point, with a ſaying of <hi>Ciprian,</hi> in his 3. <hi>Epi.</hi> If any that went before vs, either of ignorance, or of ſimplicity, hath not obſerued that which the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, his ſimplicity through the Lords indulgence may bee pardoned; but we, whom the Lord hath taught, and inſtructed, cannot be pardoned.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3</head>
               <p>In the third place of my firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diuiſion, I thought it fit, that we ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how this noble Eunuch was buſied, &amp; imployed in his return homewarde: and that is ſet downe in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14496:35"/> the 28. <hi>verſe. And as he returned ſitting in his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, he read Eſaias the Prophet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord hauing touched the heart of this noble Eunuch, and finding that hee deſired to taſte of the bread of life, reſolued in great mercy to feede him plentifully therwith: and finding him to haue a holy thirſt after the water of life, was pleaſed to ſet open vnto him, the very fountaine, or conduits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and prouided that hee ſhould bee fed, with the very marow, and fatneſs of his holy truth, and that hee ſhould drinke <hi>de torrente voluptatis,</hi> at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well-head, the water of life, and the ſweet wine of the ſauing knowledge of his Son Chriſt.</p>
               <p>He prouided in his gratious proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that the booke of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> ſhould come to his hands: which he ioyfully receiued, reuerently accounted of, making it (as <hi>Alexander</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14496:35"/> did <hi>Homer</hi>) his companion in his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and diligently read the ſame. <hi>He read Eſaias the Prophet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what followed thereof? The Lord, who, as the bleſſed <hi>Virgin</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>filleth the hungry with good things,</hi> did fill his hungry ſoule with the beſt things, and verefied in him that ſaying of <hi>Salomon, Non perdet Dominus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam iuſti fame,</hi> The Lord will not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh the ſoule of a righteous man with hunger, but will feed it: for he fed him with the richeſt, and moſt precious cates and iunkets of his moſt holy and heauenly truth.</p>
               <p>Neither did it only pleaſe God that the Booke and Propheſie of <hi>Eſay</hi> ſhould onely and alone come to the hands and ſight of this noble Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage: but heerein alſo did Gods grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goodneſſe and rich mercy plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare vnto him, in that not by chance, or at aduenture, but by the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14496:36"/> prouidence of God, his hand was turned, and his eye directed to the reading of ſuch a part and portion of that Propheſie, as contained in it the ſumme and ſubſtance of the Goſpell; and from whence, <hi>Philip</hi> might haue a good ground, and take iuſt occaſion, beginning (as hee did) at that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to open and expound vnto him the whole myſtery of Gods mercy in Chriſt, and mans ſaluation by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The words of the place he read, are theſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 32. <hi>and</hi> 33. <hi>Hee was led as a ſheep to the ſlaughter, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words, the Prophet ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the manner and order which it pleaſed God to vſe in the redeeming of his Church; namely, by the death of Chriſt, as of a Lambe ſlaine as a propitiatory ſacrifice for the ſinnes of mankinde. <hi>That as a ſheepe he was led to the ſlaughter, and like a lambe dumbe before his ſhearer, hee opened not his mouth; &amp;c.</hi> Whereby is ſignified, that he willingly offered vp himſelfe, as a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14496:36"/> voluntary ſacrifice, or free-will offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for mans redemption vnto God.</p>
               <p>More briefly &amp; in a word, for I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not at this time to make any ſtay in the interpretation of theſe wordes in my Text (howſoeuer they be moſt worthy to bee largely entreated of) more briefly I ſay, and in a word, In theſe words of <hi>Eſay,</hi> which the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch was now in reading, when <hi>Philip</hi> came and ſpake vnto him, two things eſpecially are myſtically and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically deliuered, concerning the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt: the firſt, his Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Paſsion; the ſecond, his Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or Glorification, and that not for himſelfe onely, but for vs alſo.</p>
               <p>Which words beeing a propheſie, or prediction of a thing then to come when they were written by <hi>Eſay,</hi> are in effect repeated by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſpeaketh thereof, as of a thing done &amp; paſt, and now performed: <hi>Hee was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to death for our ſinnes, and is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen againe for our iuſtification. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:14496:37"/> 4.25.</p>
               <p>And both of theſe appeare moſt plainely, in the 53. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> through that whole chapter.</p>
               <p>Of this argument or of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh as a Prophet, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as an Euangeliſt: the one ſpeaketh <hi>de futuro,</hi> the other <hi>de praeterito;</hi> the one of that which ſhould come to paſſe, the other of that which is come to paſſe: and yet which is worthy your marking, <hi>Eſay,</hi> though he ſpeak there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as of a thing long to come, yet hee ſpeaketh of it in the Preterperfect-tenſe, or in the time paſt, to ſhew the certainty thereof.</p>
               <p>You ſee how this noble Eunuch was buſied: and you ſee alſo what end the Lord made, and what courſe hee tooke with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He went vp to Ieruſalem to worſhip, and in his returne hee read the Prophet Eſay:</hi> and it pleaſed God that being ſo buſied and imployed, the foundation and ground-work of the ſauing truth,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14496:37"/> and knowledge of God in Chriſt, ſhould be laid and built in his ſoule to his eternall comfort and ſaluation, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt beeing the chiefe corner-ſtone of that holie and bleſſed buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tu vade &amp; fac ſimiliter,</hi> Goe thou and doe the like, goe thou whoſoeuer thou art that heareſt me this day, and doe the like, goe vp to Ieruſalem, that is, worſhip God in his holy Temple, reade the Propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> or ſome other part of the booke of God, reade it when thou art at home, reade it when thou art abroad, reade it earely, reade it late, reade it with reuerence, reade it with diligence, reade it with an humble minde, reade it with an hungry appetite, reade it with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout deſire to vnderſtand it; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, reade it with the like mind with which this noble Eunuch read it, and thou ſhalt be partaker of the like bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               <p>And although it bee not enough,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14496:38"/> onely to reade the booke, or worde of God, but that there bee more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at our hands, euen to beleeue it, and to frame our liues according to the preſcript forme and rules thereof; yet ſhall wee finde by Gods bleſsing, that the frequent and diligent reading thereof, ſhall be in good time the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of better things vnto vs.</p>
               <p>A ſmall wedge, though it cannot cleaue great logges, and ſuch as bee hard and knotty; yet may it, and doth it often ſerue, to make way for greater and ſtronger wedges, by which they may bee clouen: So your often rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the word only, may make way in you, to ſome greater &amp; more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful operation of Gods Spirit, by which your knotty and hard hearts may bee clouen aſunder, and ſo made woode fit for ſacrifice, fit to be laid and vſed vpon the Lords Altar.</p>
               <p>I knowe right well, that <hi>Cathedram habet in coelo qui docet corda in terris;</hi> that he hath his ſeat in heauen, which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14496:38"/> teacheth mens hearts on earth:</p>
               <p>That it is our Sauiour Chriſt that opened the vnderſtanding of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that they might vnderſtand the Scriptures. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45:</p>
               <p>That of him, and of him onely it is ſaid, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Thou art worthy to take the booke and to open the ſeales there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he and he onely, <hi>hath the key of of Dauid, which openeth and no man ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and ſhutteth, and no man openeth. Reuel.</hi> 3.7:</p>
               <p>And therefore except hee open the doore of the Scriptures, they ſhall be ſhut vnto you, notwithſtanding you doe often reade them.</p>
               <p>Yet if you doe often reade them, you do <hi>ſtare in via, qua tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſit Dominus,</hi> you doe ſtand in the way by which the Lord paſſeth: and if you doe but ſtand in the way by which the Lord often paſſeth, it may be he will at one time or other, turne in vnto you, as he did to <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lot,</hi> as they ſtood
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14496:39"/> in the way by which he paſſed.</p>
               <p>And as the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the the houſe of the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> when ſhe had prepared a chamber for him, and a bed, and a table, and a ſtoole, 4. <hi>King.</hi> 4.10.11:</p>
               <p>So I ſay, if the Lord ſhall ſee that you ſtand in the way by which he paſſeth, and that by your often reading his moſt ſacred word, you haue prepared a chamber in your hearts, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient furniture therein to receiue him, and to entertaine him, it may be he will turne in vnto you, and ſo open vnto you the hidden myſteries of thoſe Scriptures which you read, to your euerlaſting comfort,</p>
               <p>And as here to this noble Eunuch, after he had worſhipped God, at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and was now in his returne home-warde, reading of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay,</hi> the Lord ſent <hi>Philip;</hi> who ioyned himſelfe to his Chariot, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded that Scripture, and preached Ieſus vnto him, baptized him, and ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14496:39"/> left him a moſt faithful, and moſt ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant and profeſſor of Chriſt: So if we frequently reade the worde, and meditate therein, though therein wee meete with many things we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, the Lord in his good time will ſend ſome <hi>Philip</hi> that ſhall ioyne himſelfe vnto vs, ſome godly and faithfull Paſtor and Miniſter, that ſhall open and expound either pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, or publickly, ſo much thereof vnto vs, as ſhal beget a liuely and true faith in vs, and ſhall bee needfull and helpfull to our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>But here exception may be taken, and it may bee obiected, that as hee read the Propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it not, and <hi>Legere, &amp; non intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, negligere eſt;</hi> ſo, to reade, as wee doe not vnderſtand, is but in vaine, &amp; loſt labour.</p>
               <p>The anſwer may be, that although the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> hath the ſame place, and bee the ſame in reſpect of other Prophets, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is in reſpect of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14496:40"/> the other Euangeliſts, like an Eagle that flieth an high pitch, and ſoareth, and pearcheth aboue the other birds; that is, bee full of high and heauenly myſteries, which the eye of reaſon, &amp; naturall vnderſtanding cannot pierce, or attaine vnto;</p>
               <p>Yet are there many things both in <hi>Eſay,</hi> and ſo alſo in the whole bodie and all the ſeuerall parts of the holy Scripture, that are plaine and eaſie to be vnderſtood, in which are contained and expreſſed, the power, the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the goodneſſe of God, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that dutie and obedience, that feare and reuerence, which all creatures doe owe and ought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to his moſt heauenly Maieſty, as alſo ſuch things as inuite men to faith, and exhort to holineſſe of life. And theſe things, and the like, this Eunuch did, without doubt, both of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten read, and well vnderſtood.</p>
               <p>Howſoeuer; he doth moſt freely &amp; ingenuouſly confeſs, that he could not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14496:40"/> vnderſtand that place or paſſage of the Prophet which he then read, vvhich was prophetically and myſtically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered concerning the perſon of Chriſt, and the ſaluation of mankinde by his death and paſsion: which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a myſterie, which no eye but the eye of faith, can pearce and looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
               <p>And from hence we may learne this point of Chriſtian wiſedom; Not to neglect, or careleſly to paſſe by, thoſe parts and paſſages of holy Scripture, which when we read, wee doe not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand: as if they either appertained not vnto vs, or it concerned vs not at all, to ſearch out the ſenſe and meaning thereof; whereas by often reading, ſearious meditating, and frequent and deuout praying, wee might many times with comfort vnderſtand the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon the 16. of <hi>Luke</hi> hath this ſaying; <hi>Etiamſi non intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas illic recondita, &amp;c.</hi> Although thou
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14496:41"/> vnderſtand not the myſteries that are hidden in the Scripture; yet of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reading of them great holineſſe groweth.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Ierom</hi> in his fourth booke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Eſay,</hi> and eleuenth chapter, ſaith, <hi>Frequenter euenit, &amp;c.</hi> It commeth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to paſſe, that lay men beeing igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the myſticall ſenſe, are yet fed with the plaine and ſimple reading of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>To this exhortation of mine for the frequent reading of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by the example of this noble Eunuch for the reading of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though perhaps ſome part of them be not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by vs, to this exhortation (I ſay) giue me leaue I pray you, before I ſhut vp this poynt, to adde or vſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion alſo.</p>
               <p>I loue not, I confeſſe, to be ful of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions; I delight not in publick reproofes; neither take I pleaſure in ſearching the wounds, or ripping vp the ſoares and faults of others: and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14496:41"/> yet that <hi>vvoe</hi> which the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> denounceth againſt them, that call good euill, and euill good, maketh mee afraid to acquire offenders; and maketh mee alſo bold to call error by it owne name, and to tell them plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which miſſe the right path, that they are out of the way, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
               <p>Let not my meaning be miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued: neither let that which is well meant, be ill taken. The teſtimonie of mine owne conſcience ſhall ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently witneſſe, to my ſelfe, my good meaning: and the iudgement of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſhould hold you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or miſreporting of that, vvhich ſhall be by mee truely and charitablie deliuered.</p>
               <p>There is vtterly a fault among vs; to wit, the great neglect of reading the word of GOD, both priuatly in hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and publiquely alſo in the Church and congregation.</p>
               <p>The matter were not ſo great, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14496:42"/> the fault were leſſe, if it were onely to be found in priuat houſes, and had not alſo ſet foote vvithin the Sanctuarie. And pitty it is, that Lay-men onely are not heerein faultie; but ſome of them alſo, who are Paſtors, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Gods Church.</p>
               <p>It is the cuſtome and practice of many Miniſters, who are otherwiſe ſome of them, zealous, &amp; good men, In the time appointed to diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, in the Church and publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, to curtall and ſhorten, and ſometime to omit the reading of ſuch parts and portions of holy Scripture, as are appointed to be read publiquely in the Church; And in ſtead thereof, after a few prayers, &amp; ſometime none at all, to ſing a Pſalme, and ſo preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to goe to their Sermons; as if prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching were onely neceſſary, and there were either none, or very ſmall vſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of publique reading, or publique praying, in the publique Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:14496:42"/>
               <p>Whereas theſe ought to be ioyned, and to goe together; firſt, in reſpect of God himſelfe, who is in ſome degree as well glorified in the reading, as in the expounding of his holy word. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in reſpect of that decent and comely order, eſtabliſhed in our Church. And thirdly, in reſpect of the profit which commeth therof; in that, reading and praying going before, in Gods houſe, which by an excellencie is called the Houſe of prayer, they make preaching, which followeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more fruitfull vnto vs.</p>
               <p>And ſurely, I thinke, the greateſt cauſe why preaching dooth ſo little good, is for that we are now adaies ſo little acquainted with publique rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and praying in the Church.</p>
               <p>And therefore it were not amiſſe, that many men, if they will needs be mincing, and ſhortning, and curtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, would mince, and curtall, and ſhorten their Sermons; that ſo the Lyturgie, and manner of ſeruing of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14496:43"/> God in the Church, which conſiſteth as well in reading, and praying, as it doth in preaching, might haue it due time, and due reſpect among vs.</p>
               <p>And as ſome Miniſters are heerein faulty: ſo are many men and women, their Auditors, very much to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, who thinke they come time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to the Church, if they come but to the beginning of the Sermon; making little account of ioyning with the Congregation in praying: which both in nature, in time, and in order, ſhould goe before preaching. And as for hearing the Scriptures read, the chapters, the firſt, and ſecond leſſons, the Epiſtles, and Goſpels; they think that, a matter not onely needleſſe, but ſome, ſeeing it ſo omitted by their owne and other Paſtors, hold it to be a matter of needleſſe formality; and ſome, of ſuperſtition.</p>
               <p>I am no Patron of an vnlearned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery; neither come I hither to plead the cauſe of ſuch as are ignorant and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14496:43"/> onely reading Miniſters; if the Land could be without them, it vvere no matter if there were none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but as I bleſſe God for thoſe places which are already furniſhed; ſo do I with my ſoule wiſh to all places &amp; Pariſhes that want them, ſuch Paſtors and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as know how to diuide the word of God aright, to breake the childrens bread, &amp; to giue to euery of them his portion in due ſeaſon. I am no enemy to preaching; which I acknowledge to be the ordinary and moſt effectuall meanes of mans ſaluation: I enuy not to the people of God, the bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and fruit of preaching; but yet withall, and together with preaching, I wiſh alſo that publique praying, and frequent reading of Gods word, were more vſed than they are.</p>
               <p>For although preaching be a more excellent way to winne ſoules to God, and although the word preached, be incomparably a more effectuall and powerfull meanes, for our new birth,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14496:44"/> &amp; conuerſion to God, than it is when it is onely read, and not opened, and expounded vnto vs; yet hath the bare reading, and hearing thereof, when it is read, many excellent vſes, and doth many times leaue a bleſsing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind it.</p>
               <p>Wee muſt ſo preferre or commend the preaching of the word, before the bare reading thereof, that we doe not diſgrace the one, in commending the other.</p>
               <p>Wee prefer preaching before rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, not as if wee preferred a good thing before that which is euill; but as a thing which is more good, to a good thing, that is leſſe good: for both of them are good. They are therefore too blame, that in prayſing the one, labour to diſparage the other; for by both of them the ſoule may be edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
               <p>Faith commeth by hearing, hearing by the word of God; which whether it be read, or preached, neuer worketh
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14496:44"/> in vaine; but like fire, taketh hold of all matter which is apt to nouriſh it, &amp; to be inflamed by it.</p>
               <p>Chriſt commaundeth vs to ſearch the Scriptures; not becauſe they ſtand vpon the Preachers authority, or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but for that themſelues in their owne heauenly ſtrength, beare witnes, and haue a cleere and powerful record of him.</p>
               <p>And that teſtimony of <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 119. Pſalme, <hi>Thy vvord, O Lord, is a lanthorne to my feet, and a light to my ſteppes,</hi> is not to be limited and reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely to the vvord when it is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and expounded, but is verefied alſo of the word of God in generall: and therefore of it alſo, euen then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is but read by vs, or vnto vs.</p>
               <p>It is with the Scriptures as vvith ſweet Spices; they ſmell moſt ſweetly when they are beaten, or grated, or pounded in a morter: yet are they not voyd of all ſweetnes, vvhen they are but gently rubbed, and bruiſed, or
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14496:45"/> handled with the hand: ſo though they are indeed moſt ſweet &amp; fragrant when they are diuided, and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by preaching, yet muſt we not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them ſimply to haue any ſweetnes or fragancie in them, when they are but read vnto vs.</p>
               <p>For Gods truth is in the Scriptures, not as the kernell is in the nut, vvhich by no meanes can be come-by till the ſhell be broken, for ſome parts thereof haue no ſhell at all: they are plaine; &amp; the ſweet kernell, the true ſenſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may be taſted, or attained vnto, by the ſerious and diligent reading of them onely; although ſome other parts thereof be inuolued, and wrapped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with ſhells of difficulty and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie, which muſt be broken by learned expoſition and interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>If it be obiected, that this our Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch could not vnderſtand what hee read (for, ſaith hee, <hi>How ſhould I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand vvithout an Interpreter, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14496:45"/> I had a guide?</hi>) ſo ignorant men can take little profit in reading, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word read, vnleſſe it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto them:</p>
               <p>My anſwer thereunto is, that though he vnderſtood not that part, or thoſe words of the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> which he then read, which did indeed containe in them ſuch a myſterie, as no eye but the eye of faith could pearce into, as I ſaid before; yet might hee vnderſtand many other parts of that prophecie: and ſo his bare or onely reading ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, was not in vaine, or vnprofitable vnto him.</p>
               <p>And farther I anſwer, that there is great difference between ſuch as haue neuer heard of Chriſt, of faith, or of the word of God (ſuch as are heathen people &amp; Infidels, who indeed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Interpreter cannot much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by reading) and between ſuch, who beeing borne of Chriſtian Parents, haue (as it were) ſuckt religion vvith the milke of their mothers; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14496:46"/> by continual exhortation of their Parents, and by their good example, by beeing catechiſed in the principles of Chriſtian religion, and in ſome ſort inſtructed euen of children, as they are among vs, Gods Name be therefore glorified; I ſay betweene Infidell and heathen people, and vs, the caſe is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe: for wee may euen by reading onely of the Scriptures, or hearing them read, in ſome meaſure profit in the knowledge of the truth.</p>
               <p>To conclude this point, againſt their exceptions that ſpeake againſt reading, without learned expoſition; it is moſt certaine, that Scripture read, and Scripture expounded, chapters read, and chapters expounded, ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces read, and ſentences preached on, &amp; expounded, haue all of them, one and the ſame paſſage to the ſoule, outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the ſenſe of hearing, and inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the aſſent of the iudgement and vnderſtanding: the text is one and the ſame, that is, the word of God; the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14496:46"/> Schoolemaſter is the ſame, the Spirit of inſtruction; the meanes the ſame, that is, attention; the helps the ſame, which are godly motions; the fruite the ſame, that is, peace of conſcience; and the end, though not in degree, yet in ſome proportion, the ſame, that is, edification.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4</head>
               <p>In the fourth place, I am now to ſpeake of <hi>Philips</hi> performance of that duty, and ſeruice, to which he was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Angell: <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>And Philip came thither, and heard him read the Prophet Eſaias.</hi> And, <hi>ver.</hi> 35. <hi>Hee opened his mouth, and began at the ſame Scripture, and preached vnto him Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words, wee may obſerue three circumſtances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, Gods ordinance; vvho was pleaſed to vſe the preaching of <hi>Philip,</hi> and not the helpe of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, for this Eunuch's conuerſion.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14496:47"/>2. Secondly, I obſerue <hi>Philips</hi> readineſſe, and godly diſcretion; who tooke the preſent occaſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at that Scripture which the Eunuch then read, of opening his mouth, and preaching vnto him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, I conſider what it was that he ſpake and vttered when he opened his mouth. <hi>Hee preached vnto him Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt; <hi>Philip opened his mouth and preached Ieſus.</hi> Not the Angel, but <hi>Philip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the building of the Church, it pleaſeth God to preferre the ſeruice of men before the ſeruice of Angels; and to chuſe, that his holy and heauenlie truth, contained in his word, ſhould rather be manifeſted &amp; made knowne by earthly and ſinfull men, than by celeſtiall and holy Angels.</p>
               <p>And therefore, although our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had the Angels at commaund, ſo that he could haue commaunded and imployed whole legions of them, if
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14496:47"/> he had liſted, in that ſeruice; yet in the buſines of preaching his Goſpel, and the divulgation of his holy and ſauing truth vnto the ſonnes of men, he choſe rather to vſe the help and miniſtery of men, than of Angels; of his Diſciples and Apoſtles, than of thoſe holy and bleſſed ſpirits.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> was conuerted, not by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and miniſtery of an Angel, but by the preaching of <hi>Ananias. Cornelius</hi> was wonne to the faith, not by an Angel, but by the preaching of <hi>Peter.</hi> The whole world afterwards was brought to beleeue in Chriſt, not by Angels, but by men. And here this noble Eunuch is conuerted, not by the Angel, but by the preaching of <hi>Philip. Philip opened his mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A reaſon whereof may be this: As our Redemption was to be wrought, and was performed, onely in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, and not of Angels; no more was the preaching of the ſaid Redemption to be declared by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14496:48"/> or any other creature, ſaue onelie by man.</p>
               <p>And this reaſon the Apoſtle ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to vſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18. when hee ſaith, <hi>All things are of God, which hath reconciled vs vnto himſelfe by Ieſus Chriſt, and hath giuen vnto vs the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of reconciliation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence we may &amp; muſt learne this leſſon: Seeing it is the proper and peculiar dutie of the Miniſter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Scripture, That although it be moſt true, that God who is almightie, and therefore can doe all things, and that in ſuch ſort, and after ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he liſteth, either by order, or by miracle, by means, or without means; Yet in the courſe of our conuerſion, &amp; the work of our regeneration, we muſt not expect when God will ſend an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel from heauen to inſtruct vs, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee will immediatly and miraculouſly call vs, and worke our conuerſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; but muſt content our ſelues, &amp; make our beſt vſe of thoſe meanes,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14496:48"/> which God in mercy offereth vs, by the miniſtery and preaching of ſuch, as he hath by his owne diſpenſation &amp; holy deſignment, appointed to waite vpon his Altar, to attend his ſeruice and by preaching of his word, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſonnes and daughters vnto him.</p>
               <p>And therefore, if wee deſire either to knowe, or to beleeue in God, wee muſt attaine to that knowledge, and to that faith, by the onely effectuall meanes of the word of God, and by the Miniſterie and help of ſuch men, as God hath ſet aparte for the worke of the Miniſterie, and for the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring together of the Saints, which is the inſtitution and holy ordinance of God himſelfe.</p>
               <p>For this is Gods own appointment, and his owne holy ordinance, That as children ſhould expect &amp; receiue, from their corporall Parents and Fathers of their bodies, ſuch corporall foode as is needful for the nouriſhment of their bodies; So they ſhould likewiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14496:49"/> and receiue from their Paſtors and ſpirituall Fathers, ſuch as are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God to beget them in Chriſt through the Goſpell, ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall food of knowledge, &amp; inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as is needfull for the ſpiritual nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of their ſoules, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
               <p>And this was the manner and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, in former and ancient times, they were wont to go to the Prophets, and men of God, for reſolution of their doubts, and for comfort in their heauineſſe.</p>
               <p>For reſolution in their doubts. <hi>The Prieſts lippes ſhould preſerue knowledge, and they ſhould ſeek the law at his mouth, Mala.</hi> 2.7. So doth the Eunuch, in this place, deſire <hi>Philip</hi> that he would tell him the meaning of theſe words of the Prophet, which without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter or a guide, he acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he could not vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>For comfort in their heauineſs. One example for many, The <hi>Shunamite</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:14496:49"/> trauelled to mount Carmell, to <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet, when her ſoule was full of heauineſſe for the death of her one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne; and ſhee was comforted. 4. <hi>King.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>The reaſon, why both in former, and later times, and indeed why in all times, men and women ſhould repaire to the Prophets &amp; Miniſters of God, both for the reſolution of their doubts, and for comfort in their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe, is, becauſe</p>
               <p>They haue, or ſhould haue, <hi>a tongue of the learned,</hi> and ſhould knowe to miniſter a word in due time to him that is wearie:</p>
               <p>They haue, or ſhould haue the <hi>balm of Gilead,</hi> wherewith the ſores, and wounds of Gods people ſhould be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and healed:</p>
               <p>They haue, or ſhould haue in ſtore <hi>Vinum merentibus,</hi> the wine of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation, for them that mourne and are heauie hearted.</p>
               <p>And therefore to end this point, my
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14496:50"/> exhortation ſhall bee this vnto you; When you read any thing that is hard, which you deſire to vnderſtand, but cannot:</p>
               <p>When any great &amp; grieuous croſſe &amp; calamity befalleth you, and you are ignorant of the meanes, and knowe not how to be eaſed:</p>
               <p>When you groane vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of your ſinnes, and finde the hand of God heauy vpon you, ſo that you find not in your ſelues, the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of ſound comfort:</p>
               <p>When any great and violent temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which you cannot encounter, taketh faſt holde vpon you, ſo that you finde it too ſtrong for you:</p>
               <p>To conclude, when feare and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh afflict your ſoules, &amp; your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences be troubled, ſo that you know not how to lay your ſelues downe in peace:</p>
               <p>Then deſire ſome <hi>Philip</hi> that hee will come &amp; ſit with you, deſire ſome of Gods learned and faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14496:50"/> that they will abide with you, and conferre with you, that ſo they may reſolue your doubts, and eaſe your griefes.</p>
               <p>But heere I might take vp a iuſt complaint, and lament the ſtate of theſe times, wherein there is ſo little, or almoſt no vſe at all of conference, either in ſecular learning, wherein men are loath to conferre with ſuch as are more learned then themſelues, leaſt they ſhould bewray their owne ignorance; or in points of faith, and caſes of conſcience, with Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, leaſt they ſhould thereby diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to them their errors, and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. But this complaint may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner bee made, than it can bee reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing I noted in theſe later words, is <hi>Philips</hi> readineſſe, and his godly diſcretion: his readineſſe, in that hee preſently followed the direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and appointment of the Spirit, in reſpect whereof, it is here ſaid, <hi>that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14496:51"/> he came to his chariot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His godly diſcretion, in that hee tooke the preſent occaſion, and began at that very Scripture which the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch then read, and preached Chriſt vnto him.</p>
               <p>From hence, we that are Miniſters, may learne this leſſon; To take all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions that are offered vnto vs, ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to doe good, to cut-off long and vnneceſſarie prefaces, and diſcourſes, and to go roundly and directly to the matter, not to holde our Auditors in the Church porch, when wee ſhould bring them into the Church it ſelfe, not to ſtay them <hi>in atrio templi,</hi> in the outwarde court of the Temple, but ſpeedily to leade them <hi>in ſanctum ſanctorum,</hi> into the holieſt of holies, where the <hi>Mercy ſeate</hi> ſtandeth; not to lead them along, by tedious &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſome paths, but to bring them the ſtraighteſt &amp; neareſt way to Chriſt, to take all opportunities of doing them good.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:14496:51"/>
               <p>And you alſo that are Auditours, may from hence learne, with the like alacritie and ſpeed, to heare, and to receiue thoſe good tidings and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines which are preached vnto you, and to ſtriue euen at the firſt hearing of them, to embrace and lay hold of them, with the hand of faith, as here this Eunuch did.</p>
               <p>The third thing I noted in theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter words, is, what it was that he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and ſpake, when hee opened his mouth: <hi>He preached vnto him Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe wordes I obſerue two things: firſt, here is not ſet downe at large the Sermon which <hi>Philip</hi> made to this Eunuch, neither are the words of that diſcourſe which <hi>Philip</hi> had with him at that time, here mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>Indeede it is true, that all the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14496:52"/> and exhortations of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and diſciples of Chriſt, are not <hi>verbatim,</hi> word for word, ſet downe in the Scripture, but onely <hi>per ſumma capita,</hi> the chiefe points only; and ſuch generall and chiefe heads, as the Spirit of God thought meete, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and ſet downe vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> preached to the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the priſon, and to all his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould, the word of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.32. but his Sermon is not ſet down at large: but the ſumme and ſubſtance of it, is ſet downe in the verſe going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, namely, the 30. verſe, <hi>Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus Christ, and thou ſhalt be ſaued, and thine houſhould.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 2. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> when they mocked, and ſaide that the Apoſtles were full of new wine, what time they being full of the holy Ghoſt, beganne to ſpeake with diuers tongues; <hi>Peter,</hi> when he had reprooued them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed them what they ſhould think of that miracle, and exhorted them
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14496:52"/> to haue a care of themſelues, and their owne ſoules, ſo that they began to be pricked in their hearts, and ſaid, <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall we doe;</hi> then he ſaid vnto them, <hi>Amend your liues, and be baptized euery one of you, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, for the remiſsion of ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then it followeth, verſe 40. <hi>And with many other words he beſought and exhorted them:</hi> Which many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words, are not ſet downe in that place, or there mentioned; yet the ſumme and ſubſtance, the principall ſcope of them, and the maine drift of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> is ſet downe and contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe few words which go im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before, <hi>Amend your liues, and bee baptized euery one of you, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt for the remiſsion of ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo in this place it is ſaide, that <hi>Philip</hi> preached to this Eunuch: the words of which Sermon, with all the parts and paſſages thereof, are not ſet down; as may be euidently diſcerned,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14496:53"/> in that no mention being made in this chapter of baptiſme, or of water, yet this noble Eunuch when hee ſaw wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaide to <hi>Philip; See, here is water, what doth hinder me to be baptized.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet this proueth not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be maimed, or vnperfect, as our Aduerſaries would willingly haue the world beleeue; foraſmuch as there is ſo much ſet downe in Scripture, as is any way needfull and neceſſarie for our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>So that although we haue not all the Sermons, which the Prophets, &amp; Apoſtles of Chriſt preached, word by word, and at large ſet downe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto vs in Gods booke: yet it may and ought to ſuffice vs to know, that God in his wiſedome hath ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that ſo much of their heauenly diſcourſes and Sermons is ſet downe vnto vs, as might ſerue to direct vs in the knowledge and worſhip of God, and might further Gods glorie in vs, and our ſaluation.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:14496:53"/>
               <p>And therefore there is no cauſe at all, why wee ſhould liſten to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments of Rome, or giue any care of credite and beleefe, to our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries the Papiſts, when they tell vs, that in ſom things the Scriptures come ſhort, in ſome things they are ſilent and ſay nothing, in many things they are doubtfull and vncertaine, and in moſt things hard, and full of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>With all which, and many more the like imputations, and ſlanders, they doe loade the ſacred Scriptures, onely to this ende, to make way for their owne deuiſes, and to eſtabliſh their vnwritten traditions; which they are not aſhamed to match and equall with the word of God.</p>
               <p>But let vs learne, as it becommeth vs, to put as great difference between the ſacred and written word of God, and the vnwritten doctrines and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men, as there is betweene golde and braſſe, betweene ſiluer and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14496:54"/> the duſt of the earth.</p>
               <p>And howſoeuer there was a time, wherein our Forefathers and Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were gulled, and deceiued with the fopperies, and deluſions of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written verities and traditions, yet let not vs be ſo deluded.</p>
               <p>For want of bread made of wheat, men are content to eat bread made of rie; &amp; for want of bread made of rie, to eate oaten-cakes: but yet it doth not follow, that the one is as wholeſome as the other; and when you may haue of the beſt, that you ſhould chooſe the worſt. So it is betweene the word of God, and traditions of men: when bread of wheate, that is, the worde of God, was kept away from our fathers, in an vnknowne tongue, then was bread of rie and oates ſauorie to their hungry ſoules; for the ſoule is like the ſtomacke, it muſt be fed, and it euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more deſireth ſomewhat that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to religion and ſaluation: but now ſeeing bread of pure wheat, that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14496:54"/> is, the word of God, is by Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſet before vs, let vs not <hi>inuentis fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus glandibus veſci,</hi> eate acornes when we may eate wheate; and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the holy and wholeſome written word of God, baſely feede vpon the vnſauorie, vnwholſome, vnwritten traditions, of inconſtant, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible men.</p>
               <p>But rather as it is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 19. <hi>Paul I know, and Ieſus I know, but who are yee?</hi> So let vs ſay to Traditions, the olde Teſtament wee knowe, and the new Teſtament wee knowe, but who are yee?</p>
               <p>We know the olde Teſtament, and the new; the Law and the Goſpell to be thoſe two dugges or breaſts, which yeeld milke ſufficient for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any that are babes, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>We know the olde Teſtament, &amp; the new, the Law and the Goſpell, to be thoſe two pence, ſpoken of, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.35. which are able to pay for, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14496:55"/> to diſcharge any ſurgerie, and phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, which our ſicke ſoules may need, and to heale all the wounds, all the ſinnes and tranſgreſsions thereof.</p>
               <p>We know the olde Teſtament and the new, the Law and the Goſpell, to be thoſe two ſwordes, ſpoken of, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.38. of which our Sauiour there ſaid, <hi>They are enough:</hi> for indeed they are enough, both for the aſſaulting of whatſoeuer enemies, and for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our ſelues.</p>
               <p>And therfore, let them ſpeake as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly as they can of their vnwritten traditions, and magnifie them as they liſt; we will onely build our faith vpon the holy and written worde of God: this ſhall bee our onely guide in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, <hi>Sic dicit Dominus,</hi> thus ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>And yet wee doe not contemne the voyce of Antiquitie, wee ſcorne not either the writings or opinions of the Fathers, but gladly vſe them, and reuerently eſteeme of them, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14496:55"/> giue vnto them, as much credit, as themſelues deſire ſhould bee giuen vnto them: that is, as farre forth as they agree with Gods word, wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence them, and ſubſcribe vnto them, &amp; no further; becauſe we dare not vnder their banner fight againſt God, or vnder their countenance out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face his truth.</p>
               <p>This is a good rule, In the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Fathers, that which is prooued out of the Scriptures, is <hi>Vox Dei,</hi> the voyce of God; that which is probably ſpoken and deliuered, is <hi>Vox hominis,</hi> the voyce of man; that which is affirmed falſly, is <hi>Vox ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis,</hi> the voyce of the Serpent. And as wee are to ſtop our ears, &amp; to deny all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to that which is falſely deliuered; ſo are wee not to open our eares, or to giue any farther conſent, to thoſe things which are probably deliuered in the <hi>caſe of Religion, and matters of Faith,</hi> than as they may bee either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly prooued, or neceſſarily, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14496:56"/> ſtrongly collected, and deduced, out of the written word of God.</p>
               <p>In the 3. of <hi>King.</hi> 1. when contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was between <hi>Adoniah</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> who ſhould bee King after <hi>Dauid;</hi> with <hi>Adoniah</hi> ſtoode <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt, and <hi>Ioab</hi> the Captaine; with <hi>Salomon</hi> ſtood <hi>Zadock</hi> the Prieſt, and the mighty men, which were with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:</hi> Here were Prieſts, againſt Prieſts; mighty men, againſt mighty men: <hi>Bathſheba</hi> the mother of <hi>Salomon</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this contention knew not what to doe. <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet therefore ſaid vnto her, <hi>Come I wil giue thee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to ſaue thy life, and the life of thy ſonne Salomon: ſo hee willed her to goe to Dauid the King,</hi> and of himſelfe to learne his pleaſure in that buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>Thus the caſe ſtandeth with Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this day; <hi>Adoniah</hi> ſtandeth againſt <hi>Salomon, Antichriſt</hi> againſt <hi>Christ; Ioab</hi> the Captaine, and <hi>Abia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar</hi> the Prieſt are on the one ſide, and <hi>Zadock</hi> the Prieſt, and the mighty men
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14496:56"/> of <hi>Dauid</hi> on the other ſide, mighty men againſt mighty men, Prieſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Prieſts, great men on both ſides. You therefore, like <hi>Bathſheba</hi> are diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in your opinions, and diſtracted in your iudgement: harken therefore to <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, who doth giue you counſell to ſaue your liues, and the liues of your ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; In theſe matters of controuerſie, in theſe matters of faith, goe to <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, goe to God himſelfe, looke and obſerue what he hath ſet downe in his holy word, and what hee hath decreed touching matters of faith, &amp; and hold that faſt; and as for vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten traditions, and vnwritten verities, let them paſſe, for they are not of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie to be beleeued, they binde not your conſciences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He preached vnto him Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, by occaſion of theſe words, I obſerue, that the ſumme and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14496:57"/> ſubſtance of <hi>Philips</hi> Sermon to this Eunuch, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in this one word, <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is moſt true indeed, that the ſum and ſubſtance, the marrow and pith, the power and life of all our Sermons and preaching vnto you, is grounded and contained in this one word <hi>Ieſus,</hi> the ſecond perſon in Trinitie, the Son of God.</p>
               <p>For, as all the lines which either are, or may be drawn in a round or circular figure, though they be infinit, yet all of them haue <hi>terminum ſuum in centro,</hi> they all meet, and are termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the middle point or center of the circle: ſo all the lines and rules of faith, and of religion, and all the parts of Gods holy &amp; diuine truth, though they be otherwiſe, and in themſelues, infinite; yet all of them haue <hi>terminum ſuum in centro,</hi> they all meet, and are terminated in Chriſt Ieſus, who is the very center and foundation of all truth.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:14496:57"/>
               <p>And as all the Axioms &amp; precepts of euery Art and Science, if they be rightly and duly deliuered, haue <hi>rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ad ſubiectum,</hi> a true dependence, or neceſſary reference to the Subiect of euery the ſaid Arts &amp; Sciences: ſo all the axioms of pietie and godlineſſe, all the precepts and rules of religion, and all the directions and counſels which in our Sermons and preaching either are, or can be deliuered vnto you, they haue all of them <hi>relationem ad ſubiectum,</hi> a moſt direct aſpect, and neceſſary reference to Ieſus Chriſt, who is <hi>primum et primarium ſubiectum Euangelij,</hi> the firſt and primarie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> as he eſteemed to know nothing ſaue Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. &amp; as he reioyced in nothing elſe but onely in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, whereby the world was crucified to him, and he to the world, <hi>Gala.</hi> 6.14: ſo in ſubſtance and in effect, he preached nothing but
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14496:58"/> Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Super hanc Petram,</hi> vpon this Rock, that is, vpon Chriſt, <hi>The Rock is Chriſt,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. Vpon this Rock, I ſay, did it pleaſe God not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to build his whole Church, but alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular, euery true and liuing member of his Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee are Gods labourers,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul, and you are Gods building:</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the grace of God giuen vnto vs, ſome of vs as skilfull Maſter-buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, others leſſe skilfull, wee lay the foundation, that is, wee build you vpon Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For other foundation can no man lay than that vvhich is laid, vvhich is Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. Who is rightlie tearmed a foundation, becauſe he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth and beareth vp all the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>As in a great houſe or building, the roofe thereof is ſupported and borne vp by the walls, the walls by the beames and timber thereof; and both
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14496:58"/> roofe, and walls, and beames, &amp; tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and all other parts, are borne vp and ſupported by the foundation: ſo in the ſpirituall building vp of our ſoules into a holy temple to God, the roofe, the walls, the beames, and tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that building, our faith, our hope, our adoption, the remiſsion of our ſinnes, and laſtly, the beautifull &amp; glorious roofe and couering of all this building, to wit, the decking, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, and crowning of our ſoules with ſaluation in heauen, euen all of theſe, are ſupported and borne vp by the foundation, which is Chriſt, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
               <p>Excellent, and to this purpoſe moſt pregnant, is the beginning of the firſt chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians;</hi> where the Apoſtle moſt plainly ſheweth, that our election, our adoption, our redemption, the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſinnes, and our benediction and bleſsing in ſpirituall gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that all of theſe are founded and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14496:59"/> grounded vpon the perſon of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>For our election; <hi>Bleſſed be GOD, that hath choſen vs in Chriſt before the foundation of the vvorld. ver.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>For our adoption; <hi>to be adopted through Ieſus Chriſt vnto himſelfe. v.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>For our redemption; <hi>by whom wee haue redemption. ver.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>For the remiſsion of our ſinnes; <hi>by whoſe bloud wee haue the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes. ver.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>For our benediction and bleſsing in ſpirituall gifts &amp; graces; <hi>Bleſſed be God, vvhich hath bleſſed vs in all ſpirituall bleſsings in heauenly things in Christ. ver.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christ is made vnto vs,</hi> ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>vviſedome, and righteouſnes, and ſanctification, &amp; redemption.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</p>
               <p>Runne (if you pleaſe) through the whole volume of Gods booke, take a view and ſuruey of the whole ſumme and ſubſtance of our ſaluation, and of all thoſe ſpirituall graces that further
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14496:59"/> the ſame; and you ſhall finde all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of them, wholly and onely in the perſon of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>If wee ſeeke for innocencie, it is to be found in his Natiuitie.</p>
               <p>If for purity, it is to be found in his Conception.</p>
               <p>If for freedom from the Curſe, it is to be found in his Croſſe.</p>
               <p>If for ſatisfaction, it is to be found in his Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>If for abſolution, it is in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p>If for purgation, it is in his Bloud.</p>
               <p>If for redemption, it is in his Paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>If for mortification, it is in his Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall.</p>
               <p>If for newneſſe of life, it is in his Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>If for an inheritance in heauen, it is in his Aſcenſion.</p>
               <p>If for ſecurity and ſafety at the day of Iudgement, to him the Father hath committed all iudgement.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:14496:60"/>
               <p>Laſtly, if for ſaluation, it is in Chriſt; in whom who-ſoeuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, ſhall not periſh, but haue euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</p>
               <p>In Chriſt, by Chriſt, for Chriſt, through Chriſt; ſo runneth the whole current and ſtreame of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>So doe we confirme and ſtrengthen our faith; ſo doe we back and fortifie all our hopes; ſo doe wee ſeaſon and ſweeten all our comforts; ſo doe wee intermix and conclude all our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>In the fift or laſt place, we haue to conſider the effects which this Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch's own reading, and <hi>Philips</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Ieſus, wrought in him.</p>
               <p>And they are three: 1. <hi>He beleeued.</hi> 2. <hi>He was baptiſed.</hi> 3. <hi>He reioyced; or he went on his way reioycing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he beleeued appeareth by his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14496:60"/> anſwer to <hi>Philip:</hi> for when <hi>Philip</hi> told him, that If he belieued he might bee baptiſed; hee anſwered and ſaid, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue that Ieſus Chriſt is the ſonne of GOD. ver.</hi> 37.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prima vox Chriſtiani, eſt Credo.</hi> The firſt word that euer any Chriſtian man or woman ſpeaketh, or vttereth as a Chriſtian, is, <hi>Credo,</hi> I beleeue: and till that word, with the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof be bred, and begotten in the ſoule, and brought foorth &amp; vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the mouth &amp; tongue of man, no man is or can be rightly tearmed a Chriſtian man.</p>
               <p>Till ſuch time as we belieue, Chriſt is not formed in vs: and till ſuch time as Chriſt be formed in vs, we haue no part or portion in him; wee haue no title to the couenant of God; we haue no intereſt in the promiſes of grace; we can lay no claime to Gods mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oleum miſericordiae, niſi in vaſe fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae, Deus non ponit. Ber. in vigilia na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis do. Ser.</hi> 5.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:14496:61"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fides eſt porta aurea, per quam Rex gloriae mentem noſtram ingreditur,</hi> Faith is that goulden gate, by which the King of glory entreth into our ſoules.</p>
               <p>By this gate it was that the King of glorie entred into the heart and ſoule of this noble Eunuch: and if euer hee enter into vs, and our ſoules, by this gate he muſt enter.</p>
               <p>Let me therefore vſe the words of <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto you, <hi>Lift vp your heads, ye gates; &amp; be ye lift vp ye euerlaſting doors, and the King of glory ſhall come in.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1. Effect; <hi>Hee beleeued.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Faithfull and bleſſed Prince, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and bleſſed Eunuch! great in thy birth, and thy nobility, but farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in thy regeneration and new birth in Chriſt; great in the fauour &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of thy Queene and Miſtris, beeing her chiefe Steward, but farre greater in the fauour and countenance of thy heauenly King, thy Maſter and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14496:61"/> Sauiour; great in the imployments of thy place and office, as beeing chiefe ruler and diſpoſer of a Queenes trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but farre greater in beeing of of Chriſts familie, &amp; entruſted with the treaſures of heauen;</p>
                  <p>How doeſt thou, as one placed in ſome high and eminent ſeate aboue vs, and aduanced to the higheſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; now made a Saint in heauen, preach vnto vs ſilly creatures on the earth! and how powerfully doſt thou ſchoole vs, and teach vs by thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to goe vp to Ieruſalem to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, to reade, not <hi>Eſay</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet onely, but euen the whole booke of God! that ſo vſing thoſe, and all ſuch other gratious means which God offereth vnto vs, for the illumination of our darke hearts, by faith, as thou here diddeſt, we might alſo with thee in time be enriched with that precious and ineſtimable treaſure of a true faith; That ſo as the Spirit of God witneſſeth of thee, that thou diddeſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14496:62"/> beleeue that Ieſus Chriſt was the Son of God; ſo the ſame Spirit might beare witneſſe to our ſpirits, that wee alſo beleeue.</p>
                  <p>But herein eſpecially doth he ſchool vs; and in ſchooling vs, reproue vs; and in reproouing vs, ſhame vs.</p>
                  <p>For firſt, if hee that had ſo fewe meanes, to leade him to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and worſhippe of God, doe yet notwithſtanding out-goe vs in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and worſhip, who doe abound with all gratious and needfull helpes that may leade vs thereunto, how can it but be a ſhame vnto vs?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if he that dwelt ſo farre off, as Aethiopia was from Ieruſalem, refuſed not to vndertake ſo long &amp; ſo tedious a iourney, to trauell thither, there to worſhip God; How can it chooſe but be a ſhame to vs, who will many of vs, ſcarce goe out of doores, or wet our foote in trauelling to the houſe of the Lord, to heare his word, and to worſhip him in his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:14496:62"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, if he, at one only Sermon of <hi>Philip,</hi> were brought to knowe, and to beleeue in Chriſt; what a ſhame is it for vs, that after ſo many yeares enioying the word of God pulickely taught and expounded vnto vs, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many and almoſt infinite Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons that haue bin preached amongſt vs, there ſhould yet be ſo many of vs, that are not wonne to the ſeruice of God, and faith in Chriſt!</p>
                  <p>The Lord our God as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth our good, as hee did the good of this Eunuch: The word of God is as mighty in operation now, as in former times: the Spirit of God worketh with the word preached, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually now as in former times.</p>
                  <p>The induſtrie, and deſire of Gods Miniſters, though they be not equall to the Apoſtles, and firſt Fathers of the Faith, who becauſe the Church was then newly to bee planted, had <hi>Primitias ſpiritus ſancti,</hi> the firſt fruits, and the more eminent and powerfull
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14496:63"/> graces of Gods Spirit; yet are they ſuch, as might in ſome degree of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, ſerue to beget faith now, as in former times: and yet for all this, they are but few, in compariſon of the multitude, that profite in faith, &amp; godlineſſe by our labours.</p>
                  <p>The cauſe why we cannot write vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the water, is not the want of skill, nor the fault of the pen; but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſſe and indiſpoſition of the water: So the reaſon why Gods Spirit pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth not in vs, is neither any default in God, or defect in his Spirit, or weakeneſſe in his word, or diſability in his Miniſters; but onely in men and women themſelues, who are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, &amp; fitted to receiue ſuch ſtamps, and impreſsions, as they all would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe imprint, and leaue in them.</p>
                  <p>For ſurely, were men ſo willing, &amp; ſo prepared, as this noble Eunuch was, to entertaine the Lord Ieſus in their hearts, and to receiue him into their ſoules by faith, when we preach him
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14496:63"/> vnto them, then would our preaching bring forth in them the like precious effect; and many more of them, than now doe, would by our preaching of Ieſus vnto them, be brought with this Eunuch to beleeue in him, and to bee his ſeruants.</p>
                  <p>But alas, the more is the pitie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vs may truly ſay, with <hi>Peter,</hi> We haue launched out into the deep, and haue let fal our nets to make a draught, we haue trauelled all the night, and laboured hard, and yet haue taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  <p>Many of vs, like candles, doe waſte and conſume our ſelues, by ſtudying, and preaching, to giue you light; and yet many of you, for all that, doe ſtill continue, and remaine in darknes.</p>
                  <p>Many of vs, like buſie ſilke wormes, weaue out our owne bowels as they doe in making of ſilke, that you may be cloathed in ſilke, and apparelled with the precious roabes of Chriſts righteouſneſſe; and yet, for all that,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14496:64"/> many of you chooſe rather to be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with your owne rags, &amp; with the garments which are ſpotted with ſin, and ſtayned and defiled with iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
                  <p>What can the husband-man doe more, than till his land, and ſowe his ſeed? what can the gardiner do more to his figge-tree, than ditch round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and dung it? what can the dreſſer or planter of a vineyard doe more for it, than place it in a fruitfull hill, and hedge it, and gather out the ſtones, and plant it with the beſt plants? what can we doe more, than preach Ieſus vnto you?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nullus doctor eſt dator boni, quod do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bar.</hi> Wee can teach you good things, we cannot giue you good things; we may be <hi>doctores gratiae,</hi> but not <hi>datores,</hi> we may be teachers, but we are not giuers of grace.</p>
                  <p>The Angel in the 5. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> did but ſtirre the waters of the poole <hi>Betheſda,</hi> and troubled the waters thereof; hee
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14496:64"/> thruſt no man into the poole; that was a worke to be performed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that would be healed: Wee that are the Miniſters of God, wee open and expound the Scriptures vnto you; &amp; by our diuiding the word of God, and expounding the ſame vnto you, wee moue, and we ſtirre the water of life that floweth in them: you muſt be carefull to ſtep into them your ſelues, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And ſurely, the very true reaſon, why after ſo much ſtirring and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of theſe waters, after ſo much preaching and teaching, there are yet ſo many, both men and women, that lie diſeaſed, full of ſoares &amp; ſinnes, by this poole, and by theſe waters, not onely for the ſpace of 38 yeeres, but ſome for more yeeres, and all their whole life long, neuer once offering to ſtep in, much leſſe to thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thereinto, when the waters ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are ſtirred:</p>
                  <p>I ſay, the very true reaſon hereof, is
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14496:65"/> either their infidelitie that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or their lazineſſe &amp; idleneſſe that they will not, or their pride, vvhich ſuffereth them not, to humble their hearts, and to ſubiect their wills, to the will and word of God.</p>
                  <p>They conſult their owne ſenſe and vnderſtanding, and ſuffer themſelues to be caried away with the ſtreame of their own naturall reaſon, and corrupt affections: whereas if they would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues, &amp; captiuate their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and their willes, to the will and word of God, and be wholly led and directed thereby, they might, as here this noble Eunuch did, attaine to ſome good proportion, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable meaſure of true faith.</p>
                  <p>But that which the Comicall Poet ſpake of hands, in his time, I may ſay of our hearts in theſe dayes, <hi>Corda no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra ſunt oculata, non credunt niſi quod vident,</hi> Our hearts are full of eyes, they beleeue nothing but what they ſee: whereas faith hath indeed no greater
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14496:65"/> enemy than ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregorie,</hi> in his fourth booke of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues and firſt chapter, compareth him that will not belieue Chriſt, or his Miniſters preaching and telling him of the ioyes of heauen, becauſe he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them not, vnto a child borne of his mother in a darke priſon, and there brought vp, whom ſhee telleth that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad there is great light, a Sunne, and a Moone, &amp; ſtarres, men, beaſts, trees, riuers, and ſuch like things, but he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieueth none of theſe, becauſe hee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth none of theſe; which things, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he thinketh they are not, yet they are ſo indeed as his mother infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him: So although they that haue no faith, thinke there is no heauen, no Chriſt, no Angels, no ioyes, becauſe they themſelues are included and ſhut vp in a darke priſon of ignorance, and infidelitie, and therefore ſee them not; yet it doth not follow, but that it is ſo, and our Mother the Church that ſo teacheth vs, doth not lie, but ſpeakes
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14496:66"/> the truth, and happy are all they that belieue her, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>My exhortation, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluding this point, ſhall be this;</p>
                  <p>As heere you ſee, how this noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, lent not onely his outward eare of hearing, but his inward eare alſo of obeying, and belieuing, to that which <hi>Philip</hi> preached vnto him: ſo ought wee alſo to doe, as often as wee heare the word preached vnto vs, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And if it happen, while wee are ſo buſied and imployed, either in the reading, or in the hearing of Gods word preached, and expounded vnto vs, that wee feele any good motions of Gods Spirit mouing vs to faith, let vs account of them, as the Wiſe men did of the Starre that appeared vnto them in the Eaſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 2. And as they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Starre, ſo let vs follow thoſe motions and inuitations of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to faith: for, as they following the Star, were brought at laſt euen to the houſe where Chriſt was; ſo if wee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14496:66"/> the motions and callings of Gods holy Spirit, they will bring vs at the laſt, to the houſe and place where hee is, euen to the kingdom of heauen, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2. Effect; <hi>Hee was baptiſed.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Firſt, he beleeued: and ſecondlie, or after he had profeſſed his faith, and belieued, he was baptiſed.</p>
                  <p>This is Chriſts owne ordinance to his Apoſtles; <hi>Goe yee into all the world, and preach the Goſpell to euery creature: Hee that ſhall beleeue, &amp; be baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued. Mark</hi> 16.15.</p>
                  <p>So was it in this Eunuch: Hee firſt beleeued, and after was baptiſed. So muſt it be in all that are <hi>adulti,</hi> grown to full age, or come to yeeres of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: before they come to baptiſme, they muſt openly profeſſe their faith.</p>
                  <p>It is the ordinance of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who firſt inſtituted Baptiſme, &amp; did himſelfe firſt ſanctifie the element<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14496:67"/> of water, to that holy worke or buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that water ſhould be vſed in Baptiſme: To ſignifie thereby, that as water cleanſeth the outward filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the body; ſo by the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods Spirit, which worketh both mightily &amp; graciouſly with the outward element of water, and with the word, the originall guilt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe of our ſoules, ſhould be purged and cleanſed.</p>
                  <p>Veſſels vncleane, are vnfit to haue precious liquors put into them: they be therfore firſt to be cleanſed. What liquors can be more precious than the graces of God? What veſſels can be more vncleane, than our vnregenerate and vnbaptiſed ſoules? Wee are brought to Baptiſme therefore, to be cleanſed, that our ſoules may be made the fitter to receiue graces from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue.</p>
                  <p>For, as in worldly things, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be partakers of them, vnleſſe we be borne; ſo neither can we be partakers
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:14496:67"/> of ſpirituall things, except we be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed and borne anew.</p>
                  <p>Wee come to Baptiſme, the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſinners, and accurſed: vvee returne from Baptiſme, the ſonnes of God, and bleſſed.</p>
                  <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, third chapter, and later part of the chapter, compareth Baptiſme to the <hi>Arke;</hi> yet there is great difference: for, that creature which entred into the <hi>Arke</hi> a Lion, was nothing altered, but came forth a Lion; that creature which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the <hi>Arke</hi> a Wolfe, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing altered, but came forth a Wolfe; that bird which entred into the <hi>Arke</hi> a Crowe, was nothing altered, but came forth a Crowe, &amp;c. But it is far otherwiſe in Baptiſme; for, hee that before Baptiſme, entreth into the Church a Lion, returneth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, after Baptiſme, a Lambe; he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſme, entereth into the Church a Wolfe, returneth from thence, after Baptiſme, a Kid; he that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14496:68"/> before Baptiſme, entereth into the Church a Crowe, returneth from thence, after Baptiſme, a Doue.</p>
                  <p>So this Eunuch, came from home, a ſtranger to the couenant of grace; but returned home, a ſonne, and of the houſhold of faith: he came to <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> an <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> but returned a true <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the happy fruit, and bleſſed benefit, which redoundeth to all, both men, and Nations, to whom the <hi>Lord</hi> is pleaſed in mercy to reueale him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in the power and might of his word, and in the grace and efficacie of this Sacrament: by which, as by a ſtampe, or marke ſet vpon our fleſh by our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus</hi> his ovvne hand and inſtitution, like to the mark of Circumciſion, which was ſet vpon the fleſh of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and of his ſeede, wee are not onely diſtinguiſhed from other Infidels, and heathen people, but are alſo knowne and acknowledged by God himſelfe to be of his houſhold, &amp;
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14496:68"/> to belong to his couenant.</p>
                  <p>But as for others which haue not this ſeale or mark, and are not waſhed in this Lauer of Regeneration, it is not ſo with them; but the corruption of their nature, and the filthineſſe &amp; guilt of ſin, cleaue as cloſe to their ſoules, as their skin doth to their fleſh.</p>
                  <p>Many excellent things are ſpoken of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian;</hi> that hee was a great man, honourable in the ſight of his Lord, mighty and valiant: yet it is added, that he was a <hi>Leper,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be waſhed: So although many excellent things may be ſpoken, either of the nature of man in generall, or of many excellent men in particular, which either were, or are, meere natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men, vnbaptiſed, and vnregenerat; yet the concluſion muſt be, It is a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and they all are Lepers, and muſt be waſhed in the water of Baptiſme.</p>
                  <p>And till ſuch time as they be ſo cleanſed, and ſo waſhed, the Lord ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing in them, but that which
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14496:69"/> hee diſliketh, and ſetteth not his heart or his loue vpon them.</p>
                  <p>All the Patriarches were the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob;</hi> yet he loued none of them ſo well, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> &amp; <hi>Beniamin,</hi> who were the ſonnes of <hi>Rachel,</hi> whom hee deerly loued: So, all men are the ſonnes of God by creation, but hee loueth none ſo well as his regenerate and baptiſed ſonnes; becauſe they are the ſonnes of <hi>Rachell,</hi> the ſonnes of his Church, which he moſt deerly loueth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>The 3. effect; <hi>He reioyced, or hee went on his way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The doctrine or preaching of Chriſt, is rightly tearmed <hi>Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> a ioyfull Meſſage, or gladſome tidings. So ſpake the Angell to the Shepheards; <hi>Be not afraid, for behold, I bring you tidings of great ioy, that ſhall be to all the people: that is, that vnto you is borne this day, in the Citie of Dauid, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:14496:69"/> which is Christ the Lord. Luke</hi> 2.10.11. Which moſt heauenly, moſt ſweet, &amp; comfortable doctrine, when <hi>Philip</hi> had once taught, and preached to this noble Eunuch, it was no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell though as a man full of gladneſſe, he went on his way reioycing.</p>
                  <p>For if libertie be gratefull to him that hath long been captiue; if to be made a free-man, be a cauſe of ioy and reioycing to him that hath long been a bondſlaue; if to be eaſed of a heauie burden; if to be cured of a dangerous diſeaſe; if to be brought foorth of a darke dungeon into the cleere light; to conclude, if to be raiſed from the death of ſinne, to the life of grace, and to haue our part and portion in the communion of Saints; if all, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe, be bleſsings much to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed of, and true cauſes of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be brought into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberty of the ſonnes of God; to be made the Lords Free-men; to be eaſed of the heauy burden of ſinne;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14496:70"/> to be cured of the infectious diſeaſes which ariſe from humane corruption; to be enlightened by the Spirit of God; to liue vnto the Lord, the life of righteouſnes; and to haue our names written in the booke of life; all which were offered and exhibited by <hi>Philip</hi> to this noble Eunuch, in his preaching of Ieſus vnto him: theſe things, I ſay, could not chuſe but much affect him, and be great cauſes of great ioy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing vnto him.</p>
                  <p>And as <hi>Philips</hi> preaching of Ieſus, was to this honorable Eunuch a cauſe of much reioycing: ſo alſo ſhould the preaching of the ſame Ieſus, be a cauſe of ioy and reioycing to as many of vs, as are by the mercy of God, and the labour of his faithfull Miniſters, made the happy hearers &amp; partakers therof.</p>
                  <p>For, looke, what plenty is to men that haue long liued in penury; what health is to men that haue been long viſited &amp; wearied with ſicknes; what meat is to them that haue been long
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14496:70"/> pinched, and almoſt ſtarued with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; the ſame and more, is the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and preaching of the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſurance of Gods loue and fauour towards vs in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>In whom, though the traytor <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> found no excellency aboue the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of thirty peeces of ſiluer; yet his godly and faithfull children, can, and doe finde in him, all the treaſures of wiſedome, of iuſtification, of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Samſon</hi> in the time of his extreame thirſting &amp; faintnes (euen then when he cried out and ſaid, <hi>Giue me vvater, or I die for thirſt</hi>) had taſted of that water which God miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent vnto him, his ſpirit came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, &amp; he was reuiued. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15.19. When <hi>Ionathan</hi> had taſted a little ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, his eyes were opened, his ſpirits comforted, and his body ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 14. Yet neither was the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which <hi>Samſon</hi> dranke of, nor the hony which <hi>Ionathan</hi> taſted of, halfe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:14496:71"/> ſo ſweet &amp; comfortable to them, as the preaching of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is to the fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; dying ſoules of true Beleeuers.</p>
                  <p>Great is the ioy, &amp; vnſpeakable are the comforts which the preaching of Ieſus affordeth to the children of men: the ſauour of which comforts is ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Church of GOD, than the ſauour of <hi>Libanon;</hi> and the ioy therof, like vnto the dropping of milke and hony vpon their ſoules.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Samſon</hi> found a ſwarme of Bees and hony in a dead Lion: <hi>Hic est favus qui ex ore Leonis mortui exiuit;</hi> Out of the mouth, out of the word, out of the preaching of Ieſus Chriſt, which is the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> which was dead, but is aliue, and liueth for euer, commeth ſuch ſweetnes as cannot be vttered or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued. <hi>Nemo nouit, niſi qui accipit.</hi> This is ſuch a ioy, as is not like worldly ioy, which may be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. <hi>Your ioy ſhall no man take from you. Iohn</hi> 16.22.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt, like a royall King, neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14496:71"/> any citie, any towne, any village, any priuat houſe, or into the ſoule or minde of any priuate man, but hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth gifts. And it alſo pleaſeth him of his fulneſs to giue to his Apoſtles, his Diſciples, his Miniſtres, power, and grace alſo, &amp; to make them able wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they come, and whereſoeuer they preach him, and publiſh his truth (as heere <hi>Philip</hi> did to this Eunuch) to giue great gifts to the ſonnes of men, to inſtruct them in the knowledge of God; and ſo to fill their hearts vvith ſweet ioyes &amp; heauenly comforts.</p>
                  <p>The publiſhing of the word of God, &amp; the preaching of Ieſus Chriſt, is (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh, in his 5. Homily vpon <hi>Gene.</hi>) a caſting of ſpirituall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures into the laps or boſomes of men.</p>
                  <p>The L. God grant, that my preaching of Ieſus at this time, may be a caſting or ſowing of ſuch ſpirituall treaſures and heauenly ſeed, as may bring forth in you all, much fruite of good liuing, to eternall life. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
